<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An examination of the Seasonable and necessarie warning concerning present dangers and duties, emitted from the commissioners of the General Assembly of the Kirk of Scotland, unto all the members of that Kirk. June 25 1650. Which was printed at Edinburgh by Evan Tyler, by a servant of the Common wealth of England, and a lover of the armie.</title>
            <author>Servant of the Common wealth of England, and a lover of the armie.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 114 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84228</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3729</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E608_13</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201955</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862429</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862429</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114588</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84228)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114588)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 93:E608[13])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An examination of the Seasonable and necessarie warning concerning present dangers and duties, emitted from the commissioners of the General Assembly of the Kirk of Scotland, unto all the members of that Kirk. June 25 1650. Which was printed at Edinburgh by Evan Tyler, by a servant of the Common wealth of England, and a lover of the armie.</title>
                  <author>Servant of the Common wealth of England, and a lover of the armie.</author>
                  <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly. Seasonable and necessary warning and declaration.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Du-gard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno 1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reprinting of and reply to: Church of Scotland, General Assembly.  A seasonable and necessary warning and declaration.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 25".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Scotland, General Assembly. --  Seasonable and necessary warning and declaration.</term>
               <term>Church of Scotland --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  History --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114588:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EXAMINATION Of the Seaſonable and Neceſſarie WARNING Concerning preſent DANGERS and DUTIES, Emitted from the COMMISSIONERS Of the GENERAL ASSEMBLY Of the KIRK of <hi>Scotland,</hi> unto all the MEMBERS of that KIRK. <hi>June</hi> 25 1650.</p>
            <p>Which was Printed at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> by <hi>Evan Tyler,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By a Servant of the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and a Lover of the ARMIE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>William Du-gard Anno</hi> 1650.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:114588:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114588:2"/>
            <head>25 <hi>Junii,</hi> 1650. <hi>Poſt meridiem.</hi> A ſeaſonable and neceſſarie Warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing concerning preſent dangers and duties, from the Commiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners of the General Aſſemblie, unto all the Members of this Kirk.</head>
            <p n="1">[1] <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the eminencie of the</hi> danger <hi>and the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of the</hi> dutie <hi>did not conſtrain us, wee had rather choſe to bee ſilent then to emit anie publick warning to the land within ſo few daies of the meeting of the General Aſſemblie; but wee ſhould not onely run the hazard of juſt blame from them, but alſo bee conſcious to guiltineſs in our ſelvs, if wee did not in a time of ſo great ſtreight, give warning to the Lords people both of their</hi> danger, <hi>and of their</hi> dude.</p>
            <p n="1">[1] If you had well conſidered your <hi>danger,</hi> before it was <hi>imminent,</hi> and how neceſſarie it was for you to have <hi>prevented</hi> it, by an ingenuous acknowledgment of your <hi>National guilt</hi> and juſt demerit, by your perfidious and unprovoked <hi>Invaſion</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> againſt all the <hi>Treaties</hi> which were then in force, but thereby <hi>diſſolved;</hi> and by a juſt <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> for the ſpoils and devaſtations your own Armie made where it came, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til it was deſtroyed; and for the <hi>charge</hi> this Nation was at
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114588:3"/>by occaſion of it. <hi>You</hi> might perhaps have now been <hi>ſilent,</hi> and <hi>wee</hi> at <hi>quiet.</hi> How <hi>juſt</hi> our <hi>War</hi> againſt you is, and how clearly wee are <hi>neceſsitated</hi> to it, the <hi>Parlament</hi> hath ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly evidenced in their <hi>Declaration.</hi> And though wee cannot exſpect you ſhould acknowledg it (it beeing not uſual with you to ſpeak truth to your own diſadvantage) yet the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence is ſuch as muſt needs convince you, as wee are confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent it will ſatisfie all others. And if the <hi>conſcientiouſneſs</hi> you ſpeak of bee a <hi>tenderneſs</hi> reſulting from a cleer and pure light not tinctured with the <hi>dye</hi> and mixture of an Intereſt work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a prejudice, it might have put your reflections upon an other guilt, and you might have thought your ſelvs wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of blame, that you had not given warning to your <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament</hi> and People, of ſomthing elſ to bee don beſides your condemning men to the <hi>ſtool</hi> of <hi>hypocriſie,</hi> that might have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the Common-wealth of <hi>England</hi> a better ſatisfaction, and fuller reparation for and of the effects of your perfidie, then that was like to do; and might have proved a more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual means to have prevented that danger which your own injuſtice and wickedneſs have involved you in.</p>
            <p n="2">[2] <hi>The inſolent and ſtrange actings of that prevailing partie of Sectaries in</hi> England <hi>theſe yeers paſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Warning.</note> 
               <hi>in reference to Religion and Government, are ſo well known, and have been ſo often and fully laid open in the former</hi> Warnings, Remonſtrances, <hi>and</hi> Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <hi>of this Kirk, that wee need not now take up much time in repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting the ſame. Albeit the Reformation of the Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>and the advancing of the work of uniformitie there, in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline and Government, was the great dutie that the Lord called that Land unto, and which all the people of God in theſe three Kingdoms did ingage themſelvs in Covenant to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor to the utmoſt of their power; yet doth that work ſo much deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and longed for by all the lovers of</hi> Sion <hi>in theſe Nations, and all that concern's Religion, lie in the duſt altogether forgotten and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by thoſe men; and in ſtead of the beautie and order that ſhould bee in the houſ of God, a vaſt toleration of manie groſs errors is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, whereby ſo manie and ſo monſtrous blaſphemies and ſtrange opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions in Religion have been broached and are vented in</hi> England,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114588:3"/>
               <hi>as the like hath not been heard of almoſt in anie generation: And though Monarchie and the power of Parlaments was the ancient and long continued Government of that Kingdom; yet have thoſe men u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped above the Parlament, whoſe ſervants they were; and by open violence driven away manie, and impriſoned ſom of the Members thereof, and have not onely taken away the Houſ of Lords, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed the late King, but alſo ſubverted Monarchie it ſelf, and turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Foundations upſide down, and labor to wreath the yoke of their oppreſsion upon the necks of our brethren in</hi> England, <hi>not onely in regard of that which concern's their bodies and eſtates, but alſo in regard of that which concern's their ſouls and conſciences, whereof that Ingagement that is now preſſed in</hi> England <hi>is a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and publick teſtimonie, being a ſore bondage under which manie in that land now groan; whoſe caſe and ſufferings for the work of God, wee deſire not onely to remember daily before the Lord in our praiers and ſupplications, but in everie thing to regard it as if it were our own: being confident that ſuch as love the truth, and cleav to the Covenant in theſe Lands, ſhall obtein mercie of God to bee faithfull in the midſt of temptations, and that the Lord will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to bee tempted above that they are able to bear, but will give unto them the iſſue with the temptation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">[2] The wonderful and even miraculous goings forth of the moſt wiſe and merciful providence of our good God towards us in <hi>England,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> for theſe diverſ years paſt, in this great work of delivering us from <hi>Tyrannie,</hi> and ſetling us in a juſt <hi>Libertie,</hi> notwithſtanding all thoſe ſtrong fetters in which wee were impriſoned under it, have been evidently written with the verie beams of the ſun, and expoſed to the view of the world; that there are ſcarce anie that have not acknowledged, it is his work. And for our parts, wee deſire to obſerv thoſe glorious actings of his, and with all humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to rejoyce in them. <hi>God ſee's not as man ſee's,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore act's not as man act's, nor rule's the determinations of his wiſdom, nor the efficiencie of his power, by anie of the conceptions or apprehenſions of men. That which you call <hi>The inſolent and ſtrange actings of the prevailing partie of Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries &amp;c</hi> might better perhaps bee called <hi>his work, his strange
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114588:4"/>work:</hi> And though perhaps manie in this age, whoſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular concernments have been touched by this juſt hand of God, the flowings of whoſe gall, by their rebellious ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings under their chaſtizements, hath diſabled their <hi>Icterical</hi> eyes to ſee clearly his hand, may, as you do, blaſpheme that Providence, and aſſcribe its glorious and harmonious work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the anomalous extravagancies of whom you pleaſ; yet when the pangs of this birth ſhall bee over, and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempered humors com again to a juſt ballance, even you, as well as others, ſhall ſee that it is his doing. And after-ages will ſaie concerning theſe times, <hi>What bath God wrought?</hi> Wee cannot denie, but you have been verie frequent in your <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings,</hi> and <hi>Remonſtrances,</hi> and <hi>Declarations,</hi> which you have filled with <hi>impertinencies, calumnies,</hi> and <hi>ſlanders</hi> againſt the people of this Nation, obtruding, without bluſhing, obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions formerly anſwered, to abuſe the ſimple, and draw them into capital danger. And indeed you ſhould have don well to have ſpared this time from ſuch imploiment, and beſtowed it upon that in which at preſent you are more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay, <hi>The reformation of the Kirk of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> (wee ſuppoſe you mean it in your own ſenſ) the <hi>work of uniformitie</hi> &amp;c. <hi>was the great dutie that God called this Land unto &amp;c.</hi> Wee cannot but lament to ſee how miſerably you are enchanted, and impriſoned within your circle of forms, ſo as you can neither ſpeak nor think of anie thing, but this nauſeated ſtuff; how great is the judgment of God upon your <hi>hypocritical formalitie,</hi> that hee hath taken from you the ſenſ of everie thing elſ. Can you think that <hi>Presbyteries,</hi> whether in Kirk-Seſſions, Claſſes, or Provincial or General Aſſemblies, is the great Work of Reformation that God call's men to? and to the exerciſe of your effectleſs <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> as to all true Reformation? What is the <hi>uniformitie</hi> of <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline</hi> you ſpeak of? is it that conteined in your <hi>Catechiſm</hi> and <hi>Directorie?</hi> can you perſuade us to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev there is ſuch a perfection in theſe, as there is no poſſible diſcoverie beyond, or may none adventure to make it, unleſs
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114588:4"/>you bee the Pilots? Wee like better S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul's</hi> profeſſion of his judgment and practice, <hi>hee forgat what was behinde, and preſſed forward to what was before,</hi> and did not think hee had yet <hi>atteined.</hi> And upon that ground wee dare not think you have. But you quarrel the light which you cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend; and preſs for an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformitie</hi> of vvhich your ſelvs vvill bee the Meaſure, and ſet the Rules; leſt if anie ſhould preſume to knovv more, and hold it forth to the vvorld, the appearance and Coruſcation of theſe clearer Beams ſhould demonſtrate the light that is in you to bee Comparative darkneſs.</p>
            <p>Wee rather believ the <hi>great Work</hi> that God call's everie Man unto, is, <hi>to bee holie, as hee is holie,</hi> in <hi>all manner of conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation.</hi> And for an atteinment of it, by a full and unreſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſelf-denial, to go out of himſelf, and all ſelf-value, and by a moſt intimate retirement into himſelf, and impartial ſearch of his own heart, to take a view of his own corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and bee humbled at that ſight, and ſeek for pardon in the blood of that one ſacrifice of Expiation, and to bee clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from filth by the ſanctification of his ſpirit; To have no further a vvill of his own; but with an unrelucting Liqueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie to melt it down into the vvill of God, mainteining ſtill a filial implicit reſolution to conform to all the revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of that vvill: ſearching the Scriptures vvith praier and humilitie, for a diſcoverie of that will from thoſe full and divine Treaſuries, and keeping the ſoul ever open, and without prejudice for recieving in the divine Illuminations of the infinite Spirit to vvhatſoever meaſure of light, and taking heed of clouding that light by indulging of Luſt; but vvith a reſolved ſtrife againſt all oppoſition walk up to that Light, in all holineſs of Converſation, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Word of God. This vvee think to bee the <hi>dutie</hi> of a Man, and this is his <hi>happineſs;</hi> And hee that thus <hi>hath,</hi> to him ſhall bee <hi>given,</hi> and hee ſhall have abundance, his <hi>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents</hi> ſhall bee <hi>multiplied,</hi> and ſo ſhall his joie. There are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries in divine things, which the Eagles eie hath not yet made. The divine and infinite goodneſs, from whom are
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114588:5"/>perpetual Emanations, hath no where limited the ſhinings of his glorious Light. It ſhine's in darkneſs, though the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs comprehend it not. There may bee a <hi>veil</hi> upon the <hi>heart</hi> even of great <hi>Rahbies,</hi> and that in reading the Lavv. Light and Truth is received by a principle of Light from the Spirit of Truth. And vvho dare's ſaie hee hath clearly, and without <hi>aenigma,</hi> ſeen all the Treaſures laid up in the Sacred Scriptures? Doth not one daie add to another in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of particular men? doth not this daie teach us even from the Scriptures the things that yeſterday wee knew not? Hee take's little notice of his own Progreſs, or make's but little, that dare at anie time of his life ſaie, hee know's all, or that ſom other may not communicate to him a light which hee hath not received: wee could therefore wiſh you would once forbear theſe unſavorie words of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformitie,</hi> in <hi>Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline,</hi> and <hi>Governments,</hi> as beeing things not <hi>edifyng</hi> in theſe times, eſpecially to men whom the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious flowing out of the Spirit of Light and Holineſs hath qualiſied as above. If theſe things bee profitable in <hi>Scotland;</hi> wee envie not your enjoiments though wee wiſh you better. Truely wee have reaſon to ſuſpect you have not the beſt waie of ſpiritual edification, your people are generouſly ſo <hi>bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barouſly brutiſh</hi> in all <hi>moralitie,</hi> and in ſo <hi>unthriving</hi> a <hi>condition</hi> in <hi>ſpiritual</hi> things: theit leanneſs wherein make's it probable you feed them with ſhells and husks, and deceiv them with <hi>formalities</hi> and <hi>Covenants,</hi> and ſuch outſide-ſtuff, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor not to diſcover the Divine Beauties ſhining forth in the face of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and the glorious garments which they wear, that are clothed with a Spirit of holineſs, who <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God in the Spirit,</hi> and <hi>rejoice in the Lord JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> and <hi>have no confidence in the fleſh,</hi> and <hi>who make no proviſion to fulfil the luſts of it.</hi> If this Beautie were diſcovered, it would irreſiſtably draw a love: for faculties are ever ſtronglyeſt carried to their more excellent objects: they would then loath your <hi>Onions</hi> and <hi>Garlick</hi> after their reliſh of <hi>Manna</hi> in a ſpiritualized taſte. onely the danger is, perhaps they would not ſo dreadfully adore you, but look at you as their <hi>deceivers,</hi> rather then
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114588:5"/>their <hi>teachers,</hi> while you have put your own <hi>Dixi</hi> in the place of the Scriptures, or of the ſelf-evidencing diſcoveries of the Spirit of God.</p>
            <p>But you heavily complain, that theſe your <hi>formalities</hi> (which you ſay are ſo <hi>much deſired and longed for by all the lovers of Sion</hi>) and all that concern's Religion lie's in the duſt alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether forgotten and deſpiſed by theſe men. Wee know not well whom you mean by the <hi>Lovers of Sion;</hi> but it ſeem's by your deſcription, they ſhould bee ſom that are in love with your outſide Worſhip: nor what you mean by that <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> which lie's ſo forgotten and in the duſt. Wee deſire to bleſs God, that through his goodneſs and free diſcoveries of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, there are great numbers among us that are <hi>lovers</hi> of the <hi>beautie of holineſs,</hi> and by the power of that love carried out to the contemplation of that glorie of him who is glorious in holineſs, ſhining forth in the face of Jeſus Chriſt, ſo as they are transform'd into the Image of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it, from glorie to glorie, by the Spirit of the Lord; and by this means they give up themſelvs to a willing ſubjection to the power of Religion and godlineſs; and are not indeed much taken with your <hi>forms,</hi> which, in competition with <hi>power,</hi> they think may bee little eſteem'd; and do believ they are much to bee pittied, whoſe moſt ſpiritual contemplations have no ſublimer ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. Wee acknowledg with you, there ſhould bee <hi>beautie</hi> and <hi>order</hi> in the Houſ of God; and ſo there will bee, where none but <hi>ſtones elect and precious</hi> are built upon the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and when thoſe are formed and fitted, by that Spirit who onely hath the clear view of that Archetypal <hi>Idea,</hi> the pattern in the mount, according to which the Houſ you ſpeak of is to bee modell'd. And certainly if you had not taken a vaſt libertie to <hi>affirm boldly</hi> of what you know not, and to <hi>accuſe</hi> upon hear-ſay thoſe with whoſe converſation you were never acquainted, you would not thus laſh out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe exorbitant generalities, by which you get little credit to your ſelvs, or to your cauſ, unleſs with thoſe who dare not ſay, they believ you not, leaſt they ſhould incur the Churches Cenſure, the conſequence whereof is more then
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114588:6"/>they are willing to loſe. But wee cannot let you paſs thus with this <hi>calumnie;</hi> why did you not aſſign a catalogue of theſe <hi>errors,</hi> or at leaſt ſom of the groſſeſt? for your gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals ſignifie nothing; till then wee may, with much more charitie, ſuſpect you are of thoſe that call the <hi>good evil,</hi> and the <hi>evil good;</hi> that put <hi>light for darkneſs,</hi> and <hi>darkneſs for light.</hi> If you did believ them errors, why did you not name them? perhaps other men would not have been full of your minds; but if wee <hi>conceiv</hi> them to bee <hi>errors,</hi> wee ſhall <hi>confeſs</hi> them ſuch, and bee verie willing to bee <hi>convinced;</hi> for wee profeſs Our ſelvs to bee <hi>lovers</hi> and <hi>followers</hi> of <hi>truth;</hi> onely wee can take nothing for ſuch upon your word; that is onely your prerogative on the other ſide of <hi>Tweed,</hi> where the people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev you poſſeſs the <hi>infallible chair.</hi> Wee ſhall not impute it to the tenderneſs of your charitie, that you ſpare us the <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars,</hi> while you load us with your <hi>generals,</hi> interpretable to whatever your credulous Reader pleaſeth, which cannot bee ſmall matters, when they are called <hi>groſs errors, monſtrous blaſphemies,</hi> and <hi>ſtrange opinions</hi> in Religion, ſuch as hath not been heard of almoſt in anie generation. Wee think it ſtrange none of them are named; certainly you might have ſpared a line for it, from ſom of your following impertinencies, if you had not thought this courſ would have ſerved your turn better. But that you may not miſtake us, wee denie not there may bee, and doubtleſs there arc errors among us; wee are not <hi>perfectiſts,</hi> wee ſee but in part; much truth may bee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide our obſervation, and beyond our meaſure; and what is affirmed that is not truth, is error; error being nothing elſ but a deviation from truth: But where is the <hi>toleration</hi> for this all this while? what mean you by the <hi>allowance</hi> of them? If you mean wee do not hang up all that do not believ as the Kirk of <hi>Scotland</hi> believ, wee confeſs wee do not ſo pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, and think wee ought not; and are content they ſtig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matize this for one of our <hi>errors,</hi> and let it lead the Van in the Catalogue: Wee think wee ought not to puniſh men, becauſ they are no wiſer then God hath made them, and for that they do not profeſs they know and believ things which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114588:6"/>fleſh and blood cannot reveal unto them? But is this to <hi>tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> them? Wee profeſs all fit means ſhould bee uſed to give them light, by holding forth the truth in love, and in evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and demonſtration of the Spirit, and wait with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence till God ſhall reveal the truth to them: But wee conceiv that neither the gallows, nor the whip, nor a mulct, nor their Church-cenſure, are inſtituted <hi>Ordinances,</hi> or ſanctified <hi>means</hi> for conveying and evidencing of <hi>truth,</hi> and convincing and eradicating of ſtrange opinions. But for the <hi>blaſphemies,</hi> wee know not what they mean by them; If that curſed wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of prophane ſwearing bee the thing they mean, wee have certainly Laws for the puniſhment of that, which if they were in force in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and daily executed, where <hi>Oaths</hi> and <hi>Execrations</hi> are the <hi>Schemes</hi> and <hi>Elegancies</hi> of their <hi>Idiome,</hi> it would bring a good part of the Revenues of moſt among them into the <hi>Exchequer</hi> of the <hi>poor mans box,</hi> who would bee better relieved by their <hi>blaſphemies,</hi> then by their <hi>charities;</hi> you cannot but take notice that this wicked cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom is among you, and that there are verie few free; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what the ſearcher of hearts ſaid, <hi>Thou hypocrite, firſt pull out the beam out of thine own eye, and then thou ſhalt ſee more clearly to full out the mote out of thy brothers eye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But for what follow's, the Commiſſioners of the <hi>Kirk</hi> would bee asked, if they bee not beſide their Commiſſion? 'Tis verie much doubted whether theſe things bee cognoſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at their Tribunal, or whether they com under the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the keys. What hath the <hi>Kirk</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or the <hi>people</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> to do with the <hi>Civil</hi> Government of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land?</hi> And certainly, as to them, this piece of their book might paſs without anie further anſwer, but onely to unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv ſom among our ſelvs, and to diſcover the tendencie of this their hypocritical Paper, wherein they would eſpouſ the quarrel of all the diſcontents; and with their emptie blown bladders offer their aſſiſtance to buoy up everie ſink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing intereſt: They will bee the defenders of <hi>Monarchie,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of the removal of the <hi>Houſ of Lords,</hi> of the pretended injurie don to the <hi>ſecluded Members,</hi> take upon them to <hi>deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:114588:7"/>what are <hi>foundations,</hi> and bewail their renverſment; Tender they are alſo and ſenſible of the <hi>yoak</hi> of <hi>oppreſſion</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the necks of their Brethren in <hi>England,</hi> by the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. By all this they hope to draw all theſe parties to join with them for recoverie of what they have been juſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted of, and to have a partie correſponding with their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the better to effect their deſign upon us. But all theſe points have been ſo largely handled, and objections anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in ſeveral Tracts, that wee ſhall not here epitomize, or recapitulate: Onely wee muſt ask whether they bee fit to object theſe things, if they were otherwiſe of their cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance. Wee ſhall ask them a few queſtions anent theſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, and by their anſwers (if they will make anie) ſee how much of this is practiſed in <hi>Scotland;</hi> and whether they do not <hi>condemn</hi> in <hi>us</hi> what they <hi>allow</hi> and approve of in <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs:</hi> Wee ſhall <hi>firſt</hi> ask them, how much the late <hi>King</hi> was a <hi>Monarch</hi> among them after the beginning of theſe troubles? how far his commands had place among them? whether Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament and General Aſſemblies were not called without his Autoritie, and held without the preſence of his Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioner? whether this were wont to bee ſo with them? whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this bee not an innovation? and where is their Charter of privilege, that they onely of all other Nations, when they finde it good and neceſſarie for them, may change their form of adminiſtration in Government? and exclude all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who have intrinſecally a power in nature, to chooſ and eſtabliſh ſuch a Government as they judg moſt condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing to the end of its ordination, the <hi>good of the people;</hi> and to change it in whoſe or in part, when it ſhall degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and not ſerv the end of its inſtitution: or when an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other ſhall bee diſcovered that will do it better. <hi>They</hi> have don ſo in <hi>part,</hi> and <hi>wee</hi> have don ſo (as to <hi>Monarchie</hi>) in the <hi>whole.</hi> Wee are not bound to take from them the meaſure of our change; and wee are confident wee ſhall not follow their example in their <hi>returning</hi> to their <hi>vomit.</hi> And it ſeem's they were not ſo ſatisfied of their <hi>King,</hi> that they durſt truſt him without a <hi>Treatie,</hi> and a previous Agreement, <hi>limiting</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:114588:7"/>his power; but with us hee muſt bee <hi>abſolute;</hi> a <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice</hi> will ſerv them, but here hee muſt bee a <hi>grand Signior,</hi> a <hi>Sophie,</hi> or a <hi>Mogull:</hi> But wee know the meaning, good <hi>offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> profuſe <hi>gifts,</hi> and an accountles <hi>privie purſ</hi> are fine things, not to bee had by <hi>Scots</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and they may ſet their hearts at reſt for having the like anie more. Wee know <hi>Kings</hi> too vvell to bee troubled vvith them any more: Wee knovv Princes are not ſuch either conſcientious or tame things, as to bee bound by Treaties, or to value any of their miſ-called con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions longer than they ſerv their ovvn profit, which they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies contra-diſtinguiſh from that of the people. Wee vvould alſo ask theſe Commiſſioners of the Kirk, vvhether they have not an inſpection into all their <hi>Kings</hi> actions? Whether hee bee a ſheep without their fold? and without their care? If hee go aſtray muſt not hee bee brought home with a wholſome cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure? Whether any of his moſt publick actions will not com under your conſideration, as they are his dutie to God, as a Chriſtian Magiſtrate, of which you onely will bee the Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges? And upon that ground controle, direct, and cenſure him? And certainly from this your paper, wee have reaſon to ſuppoſe theſe will bee your actings: for why ſhould you bee more modeſt at home, then you are abroad? for with us you take upon you to determine of all things, as if you had learned from <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> to miſ-applie to your ſelvs that Text of <hi>Jeremiah, I have ſet thee up over Nations, to pluck up, and to plant:</hi> But to return to ſuch a <hi>Monarchie,</hi> as you will allow, will not ſerv your young <hi>Monarchs</hi> turn, and that you will finde if ever hee get quiet footing amongſt you. You complain of taking away the <hi>Houſ</hi> of <hi>Lords,</hi> and hope by that to engage all thoſe to take your parts; wee conceiv moſt of the Lords in <hi>England</hi> (except ſom few that are mannaged by by your conſpiring fellows, the Presbyterian Miniſters) are more generous then to accept of a reſtitution by your means: their remembrance of the <hi>Impudence, Avarice,</hi> and <hi>Ambition</hi> of the <hi>Court-harpies,</hi> and <hi>Horſ-leeches</hi> of your Nation, make them abhor the thought of any more of your companie, who are never welcom but where you are not known.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:114588:8"/>
            <p>But you have ſom reaſon to bee tender for them, as beeing Martyrs for your own cauſ; for though that <hi>Houſ</hi> was found by manie experiences to bee <hi>dangerous</hi> to the juſt <hi>liberties</hi> of the people, and verie often to obſtruct neceſſarie and profitable things; yet 'tis like they might have ſtood longer, had they not been found to bee in your <hi>Cabal</hi> for the <hi>Invaſion</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> and in order to it had caſt out an <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> that was ſent up by the Commons for putting things in a poſture of defence; they liked it better the people ſhould be unarmed, that you might deſtroy them with the more eaſ and ſafetie. And when your <hi>Armie</hi> had <hi>invaded</hi> us (according to the Covenant, no doubt) did they not deny to paſs anie Votes either againſt you, or thoſe among our ſelvs, that as Traytors did, or ſhould adhere unto you? Was it not time to take away this <hi>Enemie</hi> of the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> out of its power to do hurt, when it was ſo dangerouſly diſpoſed to make uſe of it to that end? 'Tis true, there were a verie few of their number that proteſted againſt the <hi>perfidiouſneſs</hi> &amp; <hi>malice</hi> of the reſt; but they were able to effect nothing, and the beſt remedie againſt like evils for the future, was judged to bee its taking away. Wee muſt hereupon ask you one queſtion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this, Whether had you not once Lords of the Articles among you, who had a previous negative upon all things that were to bee conſulted in your Parlament, without whoſe approbation nothing could bee brought into debate? Theſe you judged a prejudice to your juſt liberties, and you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved them Did wee trouble our ſelvs to ask why you did it? You thought them dangerous to your libertie and ſafetie; and the <hi>Commons</hi> of <hi>England</hi> judged the <hi>Lords houſ</hi> ſo, and ſo remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them. Why not wee, as well as you? May wee do nothing but in the verie ſame kinde and degree that you act before us? How came wee into this pupillage to your preſcriptions?</p>
            <p>But why do the <hi>Scots</hi> talk ſo much of <hi>Houſ</hi> of <hi>Lords</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> when they know they have no ſuch thing in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land?</hi> They indeed meet in the <hi>Bodies,</hi> as they call them; that is, the Noble-men by themſelvs, the Commiſſioners of Shires by themſelvs, and the Commiſſioners of Burghs by
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:114588:8"/>themſelvs, in theſe they propone and debate things as well originally, as by reference; which are determined by the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor part of all <hi>collectlivè</hi> and conjunctly in their Houſ of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament, where the Lords have no diſtinct conjunct negative, but are involved in, and concluded by the number of Votes of the whole: Therefore if the Lords have any advantage, 'tis by their <hi>reaſon</hi> in debate, to <hi>convince;</hi> not by their <hi>ſuffrage</hi> which is no more then any Commiſſioner of a Burgh; Yet, theſe men will bee Proctors for an <hi>Houſ of Lords</hi> here; It may bee imputed to their gratitude, if you pleaſ (though it bee a thing they ſeldom uſe) ſeveral of that Houſe were verie much their ſervants.</p>
            <p>The next fault is, they have <hi>driven away manie, and impriſoned ſom of the Members of Parlament.</hi> Here indeed is the thing that grieve's you; your partie is caſt out, by whom you were wont to act all your fine things amongſt us; and you have no more hopes to effect any thing in Parlament, as formerly: But let me tell you a Myſterie; you have no ſuch reaſon to plead the cauſ of ſom of them, who were not perfectly your Proſelytes; but were at cloſe guard with you; they intended to make uſe of your <hi>Faction,</hi> for oppreſſion of the faithful), and good Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots under the name of <hi>Independents;</hi> which if they could have effected, they would have cared as much for your Religion, when they had ſerv'd their turns on't, as you do your ſelvs, when you have made ſuch uſes of it. Wee, who know the men, know well their Religion, though to ſerv themſelvs of you, they vvould bee <hi>Presbyterians:</hi> In the mean time en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining you in their thoughts (expreſſed in plain lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage among their confederates) vvith a perfect hatred and ſcorn. 'Tis true, the vvay, they vvere excluded by, vvas ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarie, and the cure Emperical, but yet neceſſarie; thoſe votes of darkneſs, vvhen they ſetup all night to ruine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs and the Nation, vvere a ſufficient <hi>Diagnoſtick</hi> of ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing a corruption in the vvhole maſs beyond the power of nature to reduce a right complexion and temper; and a clear indication of the neceſſitie of a preſent and extrordinarie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie, vvithout vvhich, both vvee, and you too, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114588:9"/>your ambition bred credulitie of the contrarie, had long before this time been deſtroyed by that partie, which is ſtill the common Enemie (what ever they make you believ to the contrarie) and poſteritie reduced to as bad a ſlaverie under the late <hi>Tyrant,</hi> as that which is exerciſed by you over the poor blinde people who have given up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs to the impoſitions of your <hi>Conſiſtorialor Claſſical</hi> mercies.</p>
            <p>And now wee muſt ask you, whether ſomthing more than this hath not been don in <hi>Scotland?</hi> Whether was not that <hi>Parlament</hi> which decreed the <hi>Invaſion</hi> of <hi>England</hi> by <hi>Hamilton</hi> a true Parlament? (if not, give us ſom rule by which wee may diſtinguiſh one from another) Whether that Parlament was not ſtill in beeing after your Armie was deſtroyed in <hi>England?</hi> Whether were not ſom forces raiſed againſt that Parlament? and they driven from <hi>Edinburgh</hi> while they were yet a Parlament or Committee of Eſtates by the power of that Parlament, and had a power of conveneing it again up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any Emergencies? Whether when a part of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Forces, which had deſtroyed your Armie in <hi>England,</hi> was marched into <hi>Scotland,</hi> did you not by their countenance and aſſiſtance diſſipate and disband the remaining<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> part of your Parlaments Armie? And did you not then, while your other Parlament was in beeing, call another Parlament? and orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Elections by previous rules given by your Armie, for the ſecluſion or excluſion from Elections for that enſuing Parlament, all which as you thought fit to deſcribe and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racterize? And was not your preſent Parlament thus elected? Now let's ſee how this action in <hi>Scotland</hi> agree's with, or differ's from this in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>England</hi> here was an <hi>Armie</hi> raiſed by <hi>Autoritie</hi> of <hi>Parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and <hi>Commiſſionated</hi> to <hi>deſtroie</hi> all the <hi>forces</hi> of the late <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant:</hi> Theſe underſtood of a ſort of men adhering to that Tyrant, and labouring, though without Arms, to re-inthrone him. They prevent it, they diſſipate the Conſpirators: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom, becauſ they found them not in Arms, they proceeded not to blood, they took away the corrupt part, and left that which was found to ſerv the Common-wealth, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114588:9"/>this is their Crime; and for this they are complained of, and as much noiſ made about it, as <hi>David</hi> made for his <hi>Abſolom,</hi> againſt whoſe rebellion, the Generals own execution of him (and without a Councell of War too) had put his Maſter whom he ſerved, in ſafetie. They, who quarrell this Act of the Armie, may do well to read <hi>Joabs</hi> anſwer to <hi>David,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps it may ſatisfie them. Indeed it's true, it fell out in this caſe as in all Emperical Cures, that ſom were ſecluded, and ſome have thereupon abſented themſelves, as beeing unſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied of it, which it were much to bee wiſhed were in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Commonwealth; and that thoſe to whom that work was committed had been better informed of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, which was ſcarce poſſible for them to bee in that ſhort time wherein 'twas neceſſarie for the life of our liberties, that ſomthing extraordinarie muſt bee done for cure: And wee doubt not but they now ſee a neceſſitie of what was don, though they approved not the doing; and will again contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute their ſervices faithſully to the Common-wealth. In <hi>England</hi> the ſame Parlament continu's and act's, though ſom Members be ſecluded.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Scotland</hi> Forces are raiſed by private perſons, drive away their Committee of Eſtates, in whom was the power of the Parlament, as to moſt things; disband the Armie of their Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament; do not onely ſeclude ſom Members, but ſeclude their whole Parlament, and ſet it by, and call another by the power of that Armie by private hand raiſed and commanded; and in that call ſeclude, as was ſaid, <hi>à parte antè</hi> making whom they pleaſ uncapable of Election, or of ſitting in Parlament; ſecluding what Lords they pleaſ alſo from ſitting in their Houſ: And this Parlament, thus called, is that which hath treated with their King by their Commiſſioners, and ſo humbly beſought him to vouchſafe to put his yoak upon their necks.</p>
            <p>This is the brief of both the Caſes, and now let any but themſelvs judg. But ô yee Commiſſioners of the <hi>Kirk,</hi> why did you not tell the vvhoſe truth? Were not an ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous confeſſion better then a Conviction? O that you could
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:114588:10"/>bluſh a little that vvee might have ſome hope of you! Judg your ſelvs for once, and do thus no more; do not thus dance in a net, and think to <hi>impoſe</hi> upon the ignorant; thoſe, that are knovving vvill diſcover your nakedneſs, and men ſhall ſee your ſhame: <hi>Thou hypocrite firſt pluck out the beam out of thine own eye,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Wee ſhal break proportion in this Paragraph; but how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever wee muſt have one word more to what follow's about the <hi>Engagement,</hi> about which they are grievouſly afflicted; for that it is an oppreſſion, not onely upon the bodies and Eſtates, but upon the conſciences alſo of their brethren. What is it trouble's them? they would not have people <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe</hi> to bee <hi>true</hi> and <hi>faithful</hi> to <hi>that power,</hi> under whoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, through the mercie of God, they live and enjoie (or might do, if it were not for theſe their falſ Brethren, and their ſeduced adherents) as full and ſecure a peace, and all the conſequences of it, as can bee enjoyed here below. What trouble's them in the preſent Government? are not the ſame Laws ſtill in force that were? Is not <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall</hi> ſtill open, and the Courts there both of Equitie and Law ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in their times as formerly? Is not Juſtice in all Caſes, both Civil and Criminal, brought to the peoples doors, as freely as in the beſt times part? Are not manie grievances of the former Tyrannie heretofore complained of taken off? and that great one which remain's, <hi>viz.</hi> the neceſſarie <hi>Levies</hi> of <hi>Money,</hi> is it not their own fault? might not that alſo bee taken off, if the people would ſee their true <hi>Intereſt,</hi> and keep to it? if they would cordially keep this quarrel'd En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, in beeing <hi>true</hi> and <hi>faithful</hi> to the Power that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect's them, and not bee fool'd by the Scots, and the partizans of their King, into a diſobedience, which will certainly ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine them, not more by juſt puniſhment for it, then by the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural productions of it, if they could bee ſo unhapple as to bring their endeavors into act. But what is it in this that lie's ſo heavie upon their conſciences? is not <hi>Cuſtodes liherta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Angliae</hi> as Canonical as <hi>Carolus,</hi> or <hi>Jacobus Dei gratiâ,</hi> and as effective of peace and juſtice? Is there anie thing in it like
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:114588:10"/>your Covenant? there is nothing in the declare's a judgment, there is onely a <hi>promiſe</hi> of <hi>practice</hi> of what is in the power of the partie promiſing; and hee that will not promiſe to bee true and faithfull to the power under which hee live's, will not bee extremely perſecuted if hee bee denied the benefit of that Autoritie, which hee will not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg. But let us ask, whether your <hi>Covenant</hi> was not a greater <hi>impoſition,</hi> was there nothing in that which came neer conſcience? Wee have not time to enlarge, onely let us en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, as to Eſtates; what the ſweet and meek proceedings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us were upon that thing the Covenant, worthie to bee had in everlaſting deteſtation; wherein the great Name of God, who is goodneſs, and ſweetneſs, and love, muſt uſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in an ugly perſecution: How manie were turn'd out of Fellowſhips in the Univerſitie of <hi>Cambridg,</hi> and out of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings in the Countrie, for no other fault but refuſing the Covenant? men of great learning, and unreprovable life, were removed, and men of ſignal duncerie and ignorance and ſom ſufficiently debauched put in; denie not this for your friends ſakes, leaſt I give you a Catalogue both of them, and who prefer'd them, whom at preſent I will ſpare. It was put on by your Commiſſioners, when here, and preſſed by them on all occaſions, as earneſtly as the mark of the Beaſt, no man might have command here nor in <hi>Ireland,</hi> might keep anie Office, exerciſe anie Magiſtracie, unleſs hee had ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed that Covenant; of a far other nature, both in regard of its doubtfulneſs, and its tendencie, then this Engagement. And certainly with ſuch violence was this thing carried on, that, had not the good providence of God diſcovered to our good Patriots here the foul hypocriſie of the Scots Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners, and their deſigns, to the execution whereof they went furiouſly on, under the veil of this ſtalking-horſ the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, it had been impoſed with as much Autoritie as the ſaid mark of the Beaſt, that no man ſhould either buy, or ſell, or live, who had not taken the Covenant; and 'tis a mercie worth all it coſt, that their Invaſion delivered us out of that ſnare. And yet theſe hypocrites complain of offering the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:114588:11"/>Engagement; compare them and ſee the difference. And once again remember <hi>Thou hypocrite to pull out the beam out of thine own eie,</hi> &amp;c. And for a cloſe of this Paragraph, bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded to remember daily before the Lord in your praiers that hee would deliver you from the faſcinations of <hi>Interest,</hi> that hee would give you ſingle hearts and fill them with can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, and free you from this groſs hypocriſie, and from thoſe temptations that are ſuggeſted to you from the pride of your own ſpirits, and impotent deſires of <hi>Domination,</hi> that hee would diſcover to you the extreme ignorance and darkneſs you lie under, and that hee would give you hearts to love the truth, and embrace it by whatſoever means it bee offered to your apprehenſion:</p>
            <p>And if you will do this, and do it with humilitie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation, The Lord (who is long ſuffering and verie ready to forgive, full of goodneſs, and mercie, and love, and that wait's that hee may bee gracious) may pardon the Errors of your blinde zeal, and all thoſe things that you have don in ignorance and unbelief, and deliver you from theſe tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of darkneſs.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">The Warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note>[3] <hi>This partie, after that they have acted ſuch things in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>and alſo ſore afflicted and oppreſſed our brethren in</hi> Ireland, <hi>now conceiving that they cannot bee eſtabliſhed, and that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not eat the fruit of their own devices without contradiction, as long as the Kirk and Kingdom of</hi> Scotland <hi>ſtand's in their waie, threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten us with a War, by drawing their Forces Northward, and ſending them in ſmal parties towards the Border, that it may the leſs bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned what they intend to do: And if the Lord in his righteous and wiſe diſpenſation ſhall ſuffer them to invade this Land, as it is to bee feared, that the Gangrene of their errors may take hold upon men of ignorant and unſtable mindes, who have not received the love of Truth; ſo may wee, if they prevail, look for confuſion and deſolation, and that the Pillars both of Religion and Government ſhall bee ruined and razed in this, as well as in our neighbor-land. It doth therefore in the first place concern all the Inhabitants of this Nation to draw near to God, and to mourn for their own iniquities, and for all the ignorance and prophanitie and backſliding that is in the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:114588:11"/>land, and to ſtudie to make peace with God in Jeſus Chriſt: The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance and increaſe of many of thoſe ſins, for which formerly wee ſeemed to have been humbled, doth doutleſs greiv the ſpirit of God, and may, if they bee not ſpeedily and ſincerely repented of, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken, provoke him to give us over to the luſt of our adverſaries; Our King, our Princes, our Nobles, our Paſtors, teachers, and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have ſinned;</hi> Let us therefore ſearch and trie our waies, and turn again to the Lord: Let us lift up our hearts with our hands to God in the heavens, that hee may ſpare and ſave his people, that they bee not a prey to the enemie.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">The Anſwer.</note>[3] What the things are that wee have acted in <hi>England,</hi> wee hold out to all the world; and with humilitie rejoice that God hath owned us in them, and given ſucceſs to our endeavors, and made us the <hi>Inſtrument</hi> in his hand even as a <hi>threſhing Inſtrument, having teeth,</hi> whereby hee hath caſt down Tyrannie, and eſtabliſhed to us the juſt libertie of the Sons of <hi>Adam;</hi> And hath ſhewed us ſo far his face and favor in it, as wee are confident, that hee will not onely, not pull down what hee hath begun to build, but given therein a <hi>ſpecimen</hi> of that <hi>libertie,</hi> which his goodneſs will bleſs the world withall, as a fit ſtate, wherein that Juſtice and Righteouſnes ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe it ſelf, which ſhall bee ſet up as a triumphal Arch, through which the King of glorie, and the King of peace ſhall enter into: The adminiſtrations of the Kingdoms of the world which wee exſpect ſhall becom the Lords and his Chriſts in the which hee ſhall reign, while the earth ſhall bee full of the knowledg of the Lord, as the waters cover the Sea; while you object thoſe things, wee glorie in them, and ſhall wear them as our Crown: As for the affliction and oppreſſion of their Brethren in <hi>Ireland,</hi> wee know of no ſuch oppreſſion. Wee have indeed endeavored to reduce that Iſland, as having a juſt claim to it, and to chaſtize the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels whom wee think they will not call Brethren. And wee have alſo made ſom of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Rebels to taſte of the fruit of their doings, in rebelling againſt this <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> in whoſe pay ſome of them were, at the inſtigation of their wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ignorant and petulant Presbyterie at <hi>Belfaſt,</hi> whoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:114588:12"/>&amp; ſaisfaction have not yet ſatisfied for their guilt, but a further account remain's for them to paſs: for though neither you, nor they are pleaſed to own us for a lawful power, yet they ſhall finde that wee <hi>bear</hi> not the <hi>ſword in vain,</hi> but that it ſhall bee for the puniſhment of ſuch evil doers, and for the protection of all the good people of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> both againſt them and you. But ſeeing wee ſee our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> are your <hi>Brethren,</hi> it will teach us what to think of your devotion here, who ſhall do well to take early warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, leſt neither the hypocritical proſecution of the ends of the Covenant, nor all their good meaning bee able to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv them from the hand of Juſtice. The rules of good Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment will not now allow connivence.</p>
            <p>That our <hi>Armie</hi> march Northward is verie true; but your intelligence is bad, if you conceiv it to bee in ſmall parties; It is in a bodie, and with intention to enter into <hi>Scotland:</hi> the <hi>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STICE, NECESSITIE</hi> and <hi>ENDS</hi> of which action is at large ſet forth in the <hi>Parlament's-Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and wee ſhall here repeat nothing: If you like it not, you might have prevented it; you have had fair overtures, and a long exſpectation: Next your <hi>Hypocriſie,</hi> your cauſeleſs <hi>Pride</hi> is predominate; it is that which hath gathered and bound up the rod of your Caſtigation.</p>
            <p>But your are more ſenſible of the <hi>Gangreen</hi> of our <hi>Errors,</hi> then of our <hi>Sword;</hi> 'tis indeed moſt to bee feared, becauſ the Sword may bee put up after ſatisfaction, but theſe Errors (which wee ſuſpect you mean to bee ſom opinions againſt the power and government of the Kirk of <hi>Scotland</hi>) are like to prevail as beeing the appearances of the truth of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore which your <hi>Dagon</hi> that proud Idol muſt fal, and break its neck; therefore trouble not your ſelvs for that; the times are coming you muſt fall as well as your Mother: The word is gone forth long ſince that <hi>Babylon</hi> is faln, and this remain of her power in <hi>Scotland</hi> muſt fal alſo. The confuſion and deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion you ſpeak of would bee your beautie and you happineſs, if your guilt and provocations did not hinder your beeing inſtrumental to it. Your Religion (as you call it) and your
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:114588:12"/>Government might both bee changed into better, if you were fit for it, and you com to enjoy the ſame freedom and happineſs, that by the bleſſing of God is like to flouriſh in your neighbours Land. Your next paſſage give's your ſelvs good counſel, which wee heartily praie to the Father of all mercies, that hee will give you grace to take, onely when you com to draw neer to God, and to mourn for your ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, forget not to adde to your Catalogue, which you have here made a verie brief one, your ſins of <hi>hypocriſie</hi> and <hi>pride,</hi> of which all the world beſide your ſelvs conceiv you exceedingly guiltie. That moſt ſimple, moſt pure, and all-pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrating Spirit, who is <hi>centrally</hi> everie where, (pardon this later expreſſion, it ſound's heretically no doubt in your ears, wee know you underſtand it not in our ſenſ, and 'tis uſed for them that do) is in nothing more provoked then by the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes of men walking in darkneſs, and conceiving they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon his all-diſcovering light. This hath been your conſtant way, and you have given no ſuch clear evidence, as all who run maie read, that you have ſincerely repented of it; ſearch and trie your waies, and turn in good earneſt, and God will ſo far receiv you, as, though hee doth not deliver you from the overflowed ſcourge, which hee in righteouſneſs hath decreed to bring upon you, and of which his wiſdom ſee's you ſtand in need enough; yet hee will correct you in mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, and amend you by it, and then you will bee gainers.</p>
            <p n="4">[4] <hi>In the next place,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Warning.</note> 
               <hi>As the Parlament of this Kingdom have taken care for putting the Land in a Poſture of defence, ſo wee hope that none ſhall bee ſo negligent of their dutie, and ſo inſenſible of their danger, as not to give cheerful obedience to the lawful commands of their ſuperiours, in thoſe things that concern the ſecuritie of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and peace of the Kingdom, and that are neceſſarie for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Cauſ and of their native Countrie; but that everie man in his ſtation and calling will willingly and cheerfully acquit himſelf in the diligent and faithful performance of all the duties that relate unto thoſe ends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">[4] If you had been as careful heretofore to warn your people to bee juſt,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> as here you are to bid them bee diligent,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:114588:13"/>you might have ſpared this Paragraph, to the great advantage of the people of your Land; remember what hath been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired and denied by you; had you alwaies been upon your defence <hi>onely,</hi> you ſhould not have needed to bee ſo now, with ſo much charge and danger.</p>
            <p>If wee could have believed you had anie ſuch meaning as you here hold out, it might have ſaved us a verie great charge; a ſmall Armie would have been ſufficient to have atteined our ends, if none who are tainted with Malignancy or diſ-affection to the work of God, ſhould bee permitted to bear Arms among you, or that you would not aſſociate with ſuch. But ſure this Paragraph, with ſom other, is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culated to the elevation of ſuch among us who are honeſt and conſcientious, whoſe own ſimplicitie of ſpirit, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, have made credulous enough to bee abuſed over unto your ſide; it got no faith with us, who know well enough the complexion of <hi>Scotland.</hi> As to malignancie, certainly there are not the fortieth part of the people of <hi>Scotland</hi> who are not Malignants, and not diſ-affected to that which they call the work of God. And wee know they had 6000 Horſ and Foot ſtanding, before their new <hi>Levie;</hi> are none of theſe Malignants? why then was the queſtion renewed not long before your emitting this Warning, that the Armie might again bee purged, but it hath not been don ſince: And 'tis not like but ſom of your new <hi>Levies</hi> may have a little touch of it: Have you none of <hi>Orkney</hi> or <hi>Cathneſs?</hi> You know there when <hi>Montroſs</hi> was among them, the verie <hi>Presbyterie</hi> were <hi>Cavalieriſh;</hi> wee believ the people were not much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; for often times, 'tis <hi>like Prieſt like People;</hi> and though hee made trial of more (the fate of his Maſter arreſting the courſ of his victories) yet wee ſhall take the libertie to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev, that there may bee manie more of your heatheniſh moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taniers, that may bee alike inſtructed; your Paper confeſſe's you have manie of them; and wee conceiv, notwithſtanding all this fair impoſture, there may bee a great number among thoſe of your Armies not cleerly inſtructed in, nor much affected to the work of God: But even ſuch kinde of ſtuff
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:114588:13"/>as your Armies tent into <hi>England</hi> formerly were compoſed, of whoſe qualifications wee underſtand as well as your ſelvs, therefore wee ſhall not leſſen our Forces for all your good words; which if wee were ſure you meant to keep, wee might believ your muſters would not exceed in numbers <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deon</hi>'s lapping Armie; and one Regiment of Horſ and one of Foot might ſerv our turns. If the minde of God bee ſo clear unto you in this point, take heed of going againſt it; this book of yours will bee a witneſs againſt you before the world, as your conſciences will bee before God; take heed of your apoſtacie after your ſo ſolemn engagement; hazard not your ſelvs, and bee not deſperately perverſ. You confeſs the Malignants have often fallen before the Sectaries, and you would not give them (<hi>viz.</hi> the Sectaries) encouragement by your junction; deceiv not your ſelvs, hypocriſie provoke's the all-ſeeing Majeſtie, as much as open profaneneſs; and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the Sectaries may receiv in their ſpirits a great encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, that they are ſent by God againſt an hypocritical Nation. Deceiv not your ſelvs with the <hi>Temple of the Lord,</hi> the <hi>Temple of the Lord;</hi> manie ſo exclaim and boaſt who are not that <hi>Temple.</hi> Your ſelvs in this paragraph confeſs you have a great ſcarcitie of men rightly qualified, and can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expect a bleſſing in the fellowſhip of anie other; take heed you do not as well procure as proclaim a judgment againſt the Land, which ſhall conſume it without remedie.</p>
            <p>Wee earneſtly wiſh the Eſtates of <hi>Parlament</hi> would bee ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by you, and purge your Armie of all ſcandalous men; ſure you would have verie thin Troops and Companies. Wee would ask you if manie have not given ſcandal by their <hi>drunken-healthing thanks-givings,</hi> for your Kings arrival? or whether <hi>drunkenneſs</hi> bee not a ſcandal there? in the Sectarian Armie 'tis counted one; and, through the mercie of God, is not frequently committed; and when it is, is duly puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The cloſe of your paragraph is verie orthodox, which wee cloſe with, and embrace as a ſavorie truth. But before wee leav you, ſeeing you are ſo tender of cloſing with Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, let us ask you how came you to woo the King ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly?
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:114588:14"/>to agree with him, and bring him among you, and make ſuch great demonſtration of jole at his arrival, with more drunken bone-fiers then ever were ſeen there before? Is not hee a <hi>Malignant?</hi> ſure hee was one, when hee gave <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troſs</hi> his Commiſſion to ſubdue you his Rebels of <hi>Scotland,</hi> wrote his Letters of ſpecial favor, and gave him that Order of the Garter; how corn's hee to bee purified ſince? can you perſuade your ſelvs the taking of the Covenant will do it? have you not found by great experience it doth hot cure, but palliate; why elſ ſuch frequent Recidivations? It is not well underſtood why yee ſhould with ſo much furie and indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion execute <hi>Montroſs,</hi> the ſervant, and that (becoming your ſelvs) ſomthing barbarouſly for making a war upon you, and then immediately embrace him for your <hi>King,</hi> by whoſe Commiſſion hee did it. There is ſom myſterie in this, if you would tell us what; but perhaps it lie's deeper then your own knowledg; why may it not bee, that your own <hi>hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie</hi> growing ripe for judgment, providence hath ordered, that by his permitting you one ſignal act of it more, you ſhould thereby eſpouſ the <hi>Intereſt</hi> and <hi>fate</hi> of that <hi>familie,</hi> which lies under the wrath of God, and which you will needs take upon you to defend, though you ſee none have proſpered that do ſo; that even by your hypocriſie your <hi>hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie</hi> might bee puniſhed, from the juſt hand of him who ſearcheth the heart, and take's pleaſure in uprightneſs: Though you are, yet hee is not a reſpecter of perſons; no difference of degrees is anie thing to him, who ſet's up and debaſeth whom hee pleaſeth; hee ſomtimes give's a King in wrath; and perhaps when you well conſider all things, you may have ſom ſtrange opinion, that hee hath don ſo to you; you have wooed and married an <hi>Intereſt</hi> attended with a <hi>Curſ,</hi> which will undo you.</p>
            <p>It is no great trouble to us to hear from you the name of <hi>Sectarie,</hi> having been long acquainted with the Titles and Attributes which the civilitie of your language hath been pleaſed to honor us with; and wee bear it with the greater glorie, for that it ſeem's there are few of them of your
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:114588:14"/>Nation; and ſo may ſerv for a <hi>diſtinguiſhing Character</hi> that vvhere wee are not known, vvee may not bee miſtaken for <hi>Sots:</hi> The <hi>Sectarie</hi> therefore wee take up for a <hi>glorie,</hi> as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by you, and ſhall labor to bring the Name beyond re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, not by masking under a veil of ſeeming holineſs, (which wee wonder by what ſpecial guift they have diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, eſpecially in thoſe vvhom their conſciences have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to confeſs that they walk circumſpectly) but by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on the Lord JESUS CHRIST and beeing made conformable to the Will of GOD through the ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the SPIRIT, living in that Spirit wee deſire to vvalk in it, approving our hearts to God, and our waies to Men; deſiring you would not go beyond your line, and ſtep into the Throne of God, and judg hearts, vvhere you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not blame actions.</p>
            <p>And wee muſt again deſire you to laie down that your Antichriſtian practice of propounding your ſelvs as the Rule of Truth and judg of Error. How com you to know truth better then other men? <hi>to the Law and to the Teſtimonie;</hi> for that <hi>Rule</hi> is common to us and you; you muſt take a little more pains to ſatisfie us, then you do your Scots; you ſhall put it among our Errors that vvee hold, if you will, that wee <hi>ought to trie all things, that wee may keep that which is good:</hi> you are not ſure, but ſom of thoſe things that you count Error, may bee the Truth: and why may not ſom among us have had the boldneſs or the happineſs to know that to bee true, which is not the opinion of the Church of <hi>Scotland.</hi> And leaſt you ſhould claim a privilege for the vanitie of boaſting, give us leav to uſe it for once, as well as you; and to tell you that wee have reaſon to believ that there are ſom on this ſide <hi>Tweed,</hi> to whom the Father of Lights, by the Word and Spirit of Truth, hath made as full and glorious manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of himſelf, as hee hath don to you, who dwell beyond. And though you are pleaſed in your wonted uſurpation of the Throne of God, (wherein you will ſit and judg our affections to tell us wee love to <hi>walk</hi> in the <hi>imaginations</hi> of our <hi>own hearts,</hi> and in the light of our own fires, and the reſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:114588:15"/>that follow's: wee tell you, you ſhould do better to leav our hearts to God, but withal wee muſt walk according to the light that God is pleaſed to give us; as it is in us, it is our own light; and if wee ſhould go from that to follow your light, becauſ it is yours, wee ſhould ſin againſt our light, and againſt God, and this wee are content you ſhall note for another of our Errors, That wee dare not believ that either the dictate of anie of your Miniſters, or ours either, nor the determination of the whoſe <hi>Kirk</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or of anie elſ, ought to bee the ground of anie man's judgment, bee the thing determined never ſo true, until hee hath received the ſame truth into his own intellect, and that it becom one with it. And wee are of opinion there is no error wee hold that trouble's you worſ then this. Wee denie not but there may bee manie among us in the <hi>Nation,</hi> and in the <hi>Armie</hi> too that may bee more looſ then wee deſire they ſhould: It were to bee put among the wonders of the Age that there ſhould bee an Armie ſo numerous as ours, conſiſting all of men fearing God and walking accurately, or to ſaie leſs, fully-Civil; yet this wee tell you, they that are looſ ſhall not bee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged in it by thoſe who command them; but where is your bluſhing all this while, that you dare in this manner ſpeak of the looſneſs of manie among us, when all men know there are few among your ſelvs that are not ſo? Did not you ſuppoſe that ſom of your books might com to bee read of thoſe that have felt your Armies? and converſed with your people? and that know them as well as your ſelvs; wee deſire not to give you theſe cloſe returns, but wee may not hold our peace, leaſt wee bee thought to have nothing to replie, and leaſt you ſhould deceiv conſcientious people a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, and make them believ you are the Lord's In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, his peculiar people, a holie Nation, and an Armie of Saints, and all becauſ the Commiſſioners of the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Aſſemblie have Cannonized them. Will you ſaie your almoſt general drunkenneſs and healthing for the welcom of your King is not looſneſs? or hath looſneſs another ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication in <hi>Scotland</hi> then it hath in <hi>England?</hi> What think you
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:114588:15"/>by that Action of ſom of your people, that having taken ſom of our Mariners aſhore going for water they were detein'd priſoners till they would drink your King's health on their knees: is this the received Form of praying for your King among you, do you think our Mariners were much edified with this holy converſation of your people? wee hope your <hi>Directorie</hi> of vvorſhip hath no preſcription of this kinde of praying. Pen your things hereafter a little more circumſpectly, and do not neceſſitate us to ſtir your dunghil vvhich vvill make you ſtink in the noſtrils of all good men. You impriſon and reſtrein the ſpreading of truth, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel the poor people to your Forms in which there is nothing of the power of Godlineſs; your people are ſtill ſlaves to profaneneſs, becauſ the truth is not held out to them which ſhould make them free. They are nouriſhed in an opinion that the Kirk of <hi>Scotland</hi> know's all things, whom they may conſult upon occaſion, and never endeavor to ſtore themſelvs with principles that would effect their Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; they have onely heard of God by the hearing of the Ear, but if their Eie might ſee him they would repent and abhor themſelvs in duſt and aſhes. There is a learning and knowledg which is kept in memorie and this may well bee called other men's learning, this act's but little upon the poſſeſſor: There is a knowledg in the underſtanding that is given by the ſhining in of the beams of light from the Spirit of God (for it is the ſpirit of the Lord that give's underſtanding) &amp; this act's according to its proportion by vertue of its union with the Intellect, &amp; produce's neceſſarie effects: if you would diſpoſe your people into the waie of thoſe Noëtical recepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, you would finde their profaneneſs by little and little wear away; but perhaps then alſo that dreadful reverence toward you their Oracles (which while they practiſe, all lookers on laugh at) vvould decaie too: if the <hi>Samaritans</hi> once hear Chriſt (who vouchſafe's his ſecret teachings to all who have ears to hear) they have not much more need of the diſcourſes of the woman: You tell us alſo of <hi>approving of errors in our ſelvs.</hi> Wee would wiſh you to mend the expreſſion, let your
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:114588:16"/>unſanctified zeal to multiply heads and common-places of calumnie againſt us, run you out into ſuch ignorant expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; certainly <hi>Approving</hi> in Engliſh uſe is an act of the practical intellect; do wee approve them as errors? If not, you ſay nothing; wee denie not but great darkneſs in manie things remaine's upon us, and you verie manifeſtly diſcover it doth ſo upon you too. Wee may, and you do approve manie things that are perhaps errors in themſelvs, but apparent truths to us and you. No man approve's of an error <hi>quatenus;</hi> they are little acquainted with the proportion of the intellect to truth that will ſay it receiv's anie thing under other notion. Indeed in practice <hi>Interest</hi> ſometimes <hi>ſwaye's profeſsion</hi> and practice againſt judgment. But the ſingle and intrinſecal act of the underſtanding in giving the judgment is alwaies for truth according to the degree of its appearance, and the meaſure of its own apprehenſion. As you, when you make a ſingle judgment of your King, do verily believe him to bee a <hi>Malignant,</hi> notwithſtanding his Covenanting (as you have reaſon having ſeen manie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſo before, as your ſelvs tacitly inſinuate in this Paper, of which wee ſhall remember you in due place) yet in the mean time you offer him to the people as a <hi>Convert,</hi> becauſ you hope in time to draw ſome advantage from him in order to <hi>England.</hi> Here you apprehend right, that hee is a <hi>Malignant;</hi> yet you practiſe, as if hee were not; you are not deceived in your judgement made in your underſtanding, you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand him right enough; and though you hold out to the people that hee is converted, which you know to bee an error, yet wee ſhall not ſay you approve this error, that is, receive it in your judgments for a truth; for you perfectly judg the thing is falſ, and an error. You proceed with your heavie charge generally &amp; Magiſterially enough, that wee altogether neglect thoſe things that concern the honor of God, and the Kingdom of his Son Jeſus Chriſt. What? altogether. Wee confeſs wee have neglected thoſe things too much, and have our frailties, which wee do not approve; wee are but men, and may have too much looked after our <hi>outward ſafetie,</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:114588:16"/>as you have done after a <hi>Carnal domination</hi> under pretence of a ſpiritualitie; yet wee conceiv there is more in your <hi>charge,</hi> then will bee in your <hi>evidence.</hi> And if wee com to examine the matter, wee believ there will bee a difference in interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: What is meant by the <hi>Honor of Gold,</hi> and the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Jeſus Chriſt?</hi> Wee ſuſpect wee may not have the ſame opinion of them here on the other ſide of <hi>Twede;</hi> where wee have heard the meaning is, to give power to the ſeveral <hi>Kirk-Tribunals</hi> in Pariſhes, Claſſes Provincial, and General Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, to dominere over their Brethren at their pleaſure; that it is the honor of God, that the Gods-men bee honored; indeed thus wee have not, and are confident never ſhall do anie thing for this honor, and for this Kingdom. According as wee have been taught of God, wee believ that herein is our heavenlie Father glorified, that wee bear much fruit, and become the Diſciples of our Lord Jeſus; and for that purſpoſe that wee nouriſh the ſpringings up from that root of life, which of his Free grace by the Spirit hee hath planted in our ſouls, and ever keep them open to receiv in thoſe divine influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences and emanations of life and light that flow forth from him, for the irrigation of that root of life when once planted, whereby hee prepare's further communications of truth and light, in which everie ſoul is capable of an increaſ, and ought not to bee ſtinted by anie humanely impoſed forms.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt</hi> which hee exerciſeth in this ſtate of things (for of that which is to com, there is no oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion here to ſpeak) <hi>is not of this world,</hi> nor after the pattern or manner of adminiſtration of the Kingdoms of the World, which lye in the <hi>evil one,</hi> and are acted by the prince of the power of darkneſs; but it is altogether ſpiritual, managed by the irreſiſtible power of his Spirit in the hearts of men, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his manifold wiſdom, and the various proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in ſeveral ſubjects that hee hath conceived in the eternal Idea's, according to which that work proceed's by his own efficiencie, even according to that way of working, in which hee inviſibly effect's and work's all things in the viſible Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicall world; which is a thing known onely to a few of the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:114588:17"/>children of wiſdom, unknown to you, and therefore you will blaſpheme it, and put that alſo into the Catalogue of Errors, as you uſe to do all things that either paſs your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, or croſs your carnal Intereſt. But thoſe, who are thus made the ſubjects of Chriſts Kingdom are enabled with a principle to walk worthie of it in all wel-pleaſing. They have received an <hi>unction,</hi> even the falling down of that Spirit which was ſhed upon their head abundantlie, for hee received not the Spirit by meaſure, &amp; this annointing teacheth them all things, even all things neceſſarie for everie calling, degree, ſtate of life, or condition whatſoever, either as ſingle men, or as they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute Common-wealths, or Governments. And when they meet <hi>quatenus</hi> Chriſtians, which are called <hi>Churches;</hi> in all theſe conditions, they who are ſubjected to the Kingdom of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> are inſtructed how to walk in the beautie of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs. The firſt leſſon taught them by this <hi>annointing</hi> is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie themſelvs, and not ſeek their own things, but thoſe of Jeſus Chriſt, and to walk in love, becauſ God is love. This is the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> to which wee deſire to ſubject our ſelvs, and wee long for a further manifeſtation of the power of it appearing in all fruitfull productions in the eyes of men, to the praiſ of God: Wee hope there are manie who propound this end, and preſs on to this mark, and through mercie wee hope wee may ſay manie among us have atteined ſom weak degrees of it: But indeed wee confeſs wee do not ſtrive to advance your forms in which wee can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover no beautie, but everie day doth more and more diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to us your groſs <hi>hypocriſie</hi> under them, and their rank ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor of the fleſh, and carnalitie: And wee doubt not, but the Lord will go on to perfect both what hee hath begun to do in us, and work by us; and to make a more full diſcoverie of the unprofitableneſs of your Forms, by the dailie increaſ of new light to thoſe who have been nuzl'd in darkneſs, and ſhortlie aboliſh them all at the brightneſs of his coming.</p>
            <p>And indeed though wee dare not denie, but ſeveral a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you have the ſeed of God in you, and a foundation laid through grace, whereby you are in a ſalveable ſtate; yet
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:114588:17"/>you have built ſo much hay, and ſtraw, and ſtubble upon that foundation, and ſo choaked the work of God by your ſelf-ſuperſtructions, and exaltations, and ſo grieved that good Spirit of God by which you were to bee built up, by your <hi>pride</hi> and hateful <hi>hypocriſie,</hi> that the effects thereof do not very beautifully appear in you, ſo as thoſe who ſhall compare your proceedings with the word of God (for your enſnaring and Apocryphal Covenant wee ſhall not admit to fit on the ſame ſeat as a co-judg with the ſacred Scriptures) and look to the effects that thereupon have followed, eſpecially as to the ſouls of men, muſt needs, notwithſtanding anie of your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, abhor and abominate your hypocritical formalitie. And God will execute his judgments too upon thoſe who impriſon and obſtruct the free paſſage of truth, as wel as upon thoſe which corrupt it. How far ſom of you have been hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Seducers in <hi>England,</hi> wee well remember; &amp; know alſo the tendencie of this your ſeaſonable warning that way<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber too when men will not love truth, becauſ it croſſeth their carnal Intereſt, they are given up to the worſt practice; and certainly the practical abominations of Antichriſt, as you call it, (I would rather ſay that the ſtate of the Apocalyptical Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianiſm) are among them by them by juſt judgment of God for a puniſhment of their perſecution of truth for Intereſt ſake. God branding them to all the world for none of his, becauſe holineſs is not written in their fore-heads, and engraven up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the palms of their hands, and held out to the world in profeſſion and practice; but they have a ſpot which is not the ſpot of his children; <hi>Hee that ſaith hee remaineth in him ought ſo walk even as hee hath walked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed wee muſt tell you, you are juſtly ſubject to a jealouſie, that there is ſomthing of Antichriſt among you, there is ſuch an univerſal wickedneſs among you; prophane <hi>ſwearing</hi> is your <hi>dialect,</hi> and <hi>lying</hi> hath put you into a Proverb, <hi>uncleanneſs</hi> bluſheth not in your Stools of Repentance, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps an ill remedie for that ſin to expoſe them to view, that unclean and wicked perſons may know and learn where to finde one another; have not the ſpuings of your Bacchanals
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:114588:18"/>lately flowed in your ſtreets? And whether they do not yet run down, wee know not. But 'tis like there will bee a <hi>Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation-Torrent,</hi> as well as an <hi>arrival-puddle.</hi> Your Armie had one other ſingular good qualitie when they were in <hi>England,</hi> by virtue of the Covenant, that nothing could eſcape their fingers at the remove of a march, but what was too hot to handle, or too heavie or troubleſom to carrie or drive away: For your telling us of the manie Antichriſts in <hi>England,</hi> wee ſhall return you this; Wee have in <hi>England</hi> ſom new lights concerning Antichriſt which you are not acquainted with; there are ſeveral things in which you know vvondrous little, becauſ you ſhut all nevv light out of <hi>Scotland;</hi> it's too large to bee told you in a digreſſion, and wee ſhall not go ſo far out of our courſ to make you at preſent that diſcoverie; onely let us give you a <hi>ſeaſonable warning</hi> to look well to your ſelvs, and ſee if there bee not a great deal of that ſame thing among you that you take not notice of; certainly 'tis not confined to <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Romane</hi> vvorſhip; 'tis everie where more or leſs, and groſly and formally, where 'tis little taken notice of; Wee denie not but much of it is in <hi>England,</hi> but you have taken your marks about it much amiſs, and know not at all wherein.</p>
            <p n="7">[7] <hi>The ſucceſs of that partie provs not the goodneſs of their cauſ, or that they ſhall proſper ſtill;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Warning.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord who it wonderful in counſel, and excellent in working, hath been pleaſed to put the rod of his anger, and the ſtaff of his indignation in their hand, for executing of his wrath againſt Malignant, becauſ of the enmitie and oppoſition of that generation unto the cauſ and people of God: But if they ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade this land, and exalt themſelvs againſt the Lords inheritance, and the people that are in Covenant with him, For whoſe ſake the Lord did cloath them with power for a time, for taking vengeance upon his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, Then ſhall they ſtumble and fall, and bee broken in pieces: Though the hoſt of</hi> Senacherib <hi>did prevail againſt</hi> Samaria, <hi>yet did they fall in</hi> Judah, <hi>and hee did return with ſhame, and was ſlain with the ſword in his own land. That partie hath as yet no cauſ to boaſt that God bath proſpered them in Arms againſt the Covenant, or againſt a praying people ſtedfaſt in the Lords cauſ, following his way,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:114588:18"/>and waiting upon him for help and ſucceſs: All their encounters have hitherto been againſt Malignants; and now the Lord having per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed ſo much of his work againſt that generation, who know's but the Sectaries day may alſo be coming, and that when the ſtate of the queſtion ſhall bee changed, God may turn his hand upon them, and bring upon them the judgments of a broken Covenant, as hee hath ever don to all that look that way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">[7] Wee acknowledg that greatneſs of <hi>ſucceſs</hi> neither evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence's the goodneſs of a Cauſ,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> nor give's aſſurance of its own continuance. What ſucceſs the merciful providence of God hath given to the Armies of this Nation, we deſire humbly and thankfully to acknowledg and rejoice in, and rejoice not an our ſelvs, or arrogate anie thing of praiſ or honor, which is onely due to the Lord of hoſts, in whoſe hand wee were <hi>Inſtruments,</hi> and of our ſelvs are nothing. The Lord who is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed wonderful in counſel, and excellent in working, hath been pleaſed to execute his wrath by us againſt Tyrannie, and againſt that cauſ which you have now eſpouſed: And having now called our Armies alſo to go againſt an hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critical Nation, Wee ſhall proceed with confidence that wee ſhall alſo bee inabled to chaſtize their breach of Treaties, and moſt wicked and perfidious <hi>Invaſion</hi> of this Nation. And do not think your diſtinguiſhing your ſelvs from Malignants, will bee your ſhield againſt Divine juſtice, as if there were none but that generation againſt whom his wrath were kindled: And indeed ſhould they prevail onely againſt, and deſtroy that ſort of people among you, it would leav your poor land verie much unpeopled; for wee verie well know you have fortie Malignants to one that is devoted to your Kirk. You ſay that partie hath not yet proſpered in Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Covenant. Wee need not fight with the Covenant, it is com to nothing without it; it was brought a little too near the Ark, and 'tis faln like <hi>Dagon,</hi> and there let it lye: But were there no Covenanters in <hi>Hamiltons</hi> Armie? Was not that <hi>Parlament</hi> that ſent them a <hi>Covenanting Parlament?</hi> Can there bee ſuch a thing in <hi>Scotland,</hi> as a Parlament not Covenanting? yet Dagon was then faln, and had neither
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:114588:19"/>head nor hands, it could neither adviſe, nor help. which hath Divine Ordination, and Inſtitution, when it ſhall bee idolized, provokes to jealouſie him, that will not give his glorie to another. The <hi>Brazen Serpent</hi> was <hi>ſet up</hi> by <hi>Divine command,</hi> and more wonderful effects wrought by looking upon it at Gods command, then wee ever yet ſaw your hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane invention of the Covenant produce, where it hath been impoſed; yet when 'twas made an Idol, hee is commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that brake it in pieces, and called it <hi>Nehuſhtam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Temple</hi> was aſtructure of Gods own contrivance and preſcription, and built and furniſhed with no ſmall charge, and there was in it greater myſteries then are perhaps of all men underſtood; yet when the people made an <hi>Idol</hi> of it, and put their confidence in it, crying out, <hi>The Temple of the Lord, The Temple of the Lord,</hi> while they committed all abomination, God gave up to deſtruction both it and them. You have too much cryed up the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and the <hi>Kirk</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and taught the people to truſt too much in them, for the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance or ſafetie of either of them. And while you talk of a <hi>praying people,</hi> wee are not much ſcar'd at it; conſider whether your <hi>prayers</hi> have not been your <hi>provocations;</hi> wee mean not thoſe onely which were offered up with your drink-offerings for the health of your King, when you kindled ſo manie fires all over your ſtreets, if not to the Hoſt of Heaven, yet to <hi>Liber Pater,</hi> and for the Heatheniſh celebration of thoſe <hi>Lyaean</hi> My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries: But wee mean alſo even thoſe hypocritical houlings of your ignorant crouds when they keep time to your paſſion, and the ebullitions of your dark zeal, invoking vengeance from Heaven (with a ſpirit of love and meekneſs, no doubt becoming Goſpel-adminiſtrations) againſt the Sectaries, who are men you know not, onely your ſelvs have painted them black, that you might with the more intention of heat and malice hate them.</p>
            <p>Theſe your horrible miſ-carrings have quite loſt you with all wiſe and good men; onely with ſuch Papers as theſe you ſtill baffle your own people, and keep them under ſlaverie, and ſubject them to a danger which is by everie compaſſionate
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:114588:19"/>ſpirit to bee much pittied. If you bee angrie at this plain dealing, you may thank your ſelvs; if you care not what you ſay to delude the people, wee muſt tell ours the truth to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceiv them. And let not thoſe few in <hi>Scotland</hi> who truly fear God (for wee have heard there bee a few ſuch, though but a verie few) bee kindled at this plain dealing, which the <hi>pride</hi> &amp; <hi>hypocriſie</hi> of this Paper hath neceſſitated, not leaſt they ſhould ſtill bee wiſe, not onely in their own conceits (for of that cure wee have no hope) but leaſt they ſhould ſtill appear what they are not to the judgments of others, and thereby dangerouſly deceiv them.</p>
            <p n="8">[8] <hi>Wee deſire that not onely others,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Warning.</note> 
               <hi>but the Sectaries themſelvs may conſider, that when</hi> England <hi>was verie low, and well nigh brought under the feet of the Popiſh, Prelatical, and Malignant Partie, That this Nation was then much ſolicited for their aſſiſtance and relief, and even by ſom of theſe who have ſince that time been verie active and inſtrumental for the partie which now prevail's in that land: The Kirk and Kingdom of</hi> Scotland <hi>were then ſo compaſſionate of their bretbrens condition, that they were willing to join in a League and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with them, which both Kingdoms, even manie of thoſe who are now in the Armie, did ſolemnly ſwear and ſubſcribe: In proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the ends thereof, this Kingdom did ſend into</hi> England <hi>a conſiderable Armie, by whoſe aſſiſtance the power of the Malignant Partie was broken and brought low, and the Parlament and Armie of</hi> England <hi>put into ſuch a condition, that they needed no more fear the ſtrength of their enemies. This League and Covenant, which was the foundation of</hi> England's <hi>and the Armies deliverance and ſafetie, the Armie hath now forgotten and trodden under foot, and walk in all their proceedings no leſs contrarie thereto, then darkneſs is unto light: Neither doth it ſatisfie them to do ſo in their own Land, but they threaten us alſo with war, for no other reaſon, but becauſe wee cleav to our dutie in theſe things, to which</hi> England <hi>ſtand's no leſs obliged unto by Covenant before the Lord then wee do. Wee may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently aſſert and profeſs before the world, that the Lord's people in this Land are not conſcious to themſelvs of anie wrong don to that prevailing partie in</hi> England: <hi>The engagement in the year</hi> I648. <hi>was no leſs abhorred, and teſtified againſt by the Kirk of</hi> Scotland,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:114588:20"/>
               <hi>and by theſe that are how in place and power in the State, and by all the godly in the land, then it was by that partie themſelvs; Which did ſo far convince the Houſ of Commons, that in their Letter to the General Aſſemblie of this Kirk in the ſame year, they profeſs that they are aſſured, that theſe impious and unwarrantable actions cannot bee don with the approbation and aſſent of the religious and well-affected people of the Kingdom of</hi> Scotland, <hi>and that they do underſtand, that there are verie few amongſt theſe who were in the engagement againſt them, that first engaged with them in the Covenant and Cauſ, but ſuch as are profeſſed enemies to them, however they were then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to proceed thereunto, that they might the better deceiv the people of</hi> England; <hi>And that therefore they are unwilling to impute ſuch evils to this Nation in general. It is known how manie fervent praiers and ſupplications were poured out in this Land before the Lord againſt that engagement; and wee think wee may without boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſay, that thoſe praiers had as much influence upon the defeat there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as all the power of that Armie: And ſince that time that engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath been publickly diſavowed, diſclaimed, and repealed by the Parlament of this Kingdom. Neither hath that partie anie thing to challenge us concerning Malignants, both Kirk and State having conſtantly followed, and beeing ſtill about their duties againſt them, without conniving at, or complying with them in their courſes. It is true, that this Kingdom and Kirk have proteſted and teſtified againſt the proceedings of Sectaries in reference to Religion and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; Which wee could not but do, unleſs wee had forgotten our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and the Chriſtian mutual ties that lie upon us, not onely as ſiſter-Churches, but as covenanted Churches; and ſo make our ſelvs par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of their ſins, and expoſe our ſelvs to the hazard of their plagues. Wee in this Land beeing therefore conſcious to our ſelvs of nothing but dutie; If they ſhall invade us for following the ſame, ſhall not God look upon it and avenge it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">[8] If wee ſhall anſwer this Paragraph at large,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer </seg>
               </label> wee ſhall draw out this Paper to ſuch a length, as maie ſwell it beyond the price of ſom, and the leiſure of others; wee ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let it here keep proportion, and in another tract, which is begun, give the world a full and true repreſentation and character of all their candor and fair dealing, in all the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:114588:20"/>and affairs that have been between the Nations ſince theſe laſt troubles, which ſhall proceed as faſt as leiſure will ſerv; and give but ſom touches the while.</p>
            <p>The Sectaries do verie well conſider, and remember too, that <hi>England</hi> was verie low brought under the foot of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh and prelatical partie, which were the Armies which that late King uſed to ſubdue us, whoſe quarrel you eſpouſed not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Covenant, and pleaded his cauſ, and whom you would have brought in again upon ſuch terms, as had not providence prevented the effect of your endeavors, you had ruined your ſelvs and us too. And wee remember alſo, that though you were as much concerned as wee in the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and priviledged onely with one ſtop of a greater remoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet wee were inforc'd verie much to ſolicite you by the parties you mention, whom God hath ſince made verie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental for the good of this Land, before wee could pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with the <hi>Kirk</hi> and <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> notwithſtanding our great need, and their own evident danger, either to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate us, or bee careful of themſelvs, until they had brought us into the ſnare of a Covenant; of which the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning Church knew they ſhould bee afterward able to make ſom other good uſes beſides the Reformation of Religion; and however our dangers were imminent, yet they would not com in to our aſſiſtance till wee had furniſhed them with 50000 l. a ſum of no ſmall difficultie for us to raiſ at that time, when our quarters were ſo ſtreight, and our occaſions ſo multiplied; but yet, when they had a minde to invade us under <hi>Hamilton,</hi> they could do it without anie Levie-monie advanced. What aſſiſtance they gave, and how much they contributed to the bringing us to that condition, wherein wee needed not to fear the ſtrength of our enemies, wee ſhall more fully ſet out in that other mentioned Tract. Onely now they proved a broken reed, from whom wee had but a weak ſupport; but it ran into our hands, and pierced us ſufficiently, as all places, where they came, can bear ſenſible witneſs, and which the world ſhall ſhortly know. Briefly, they took our money, and helped us little, being ſpecially careful
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:114588:21"/>to keep out of the waie of danger; they did like right mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinaries purſue their own intereſt, which was verie oppoſite to ours; wee deſired to end the war, and they to <hi>lengthen</hi> it, that they might lengthen their emploiment, hoping they ſhould never bee neceſſitated again to return to their own poor Countrie: Yet this advantage wee had, that while they took our paie for a great while, they did not take our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies part; and our monie produced with them as good ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect as the worſhip of that <hi>Numen</hi> at <hi>Calecut</hi> doth there, you know who, and what.</p>
            <p>The <hi>League</hi> and <hi>Covenant,</hi> you ſay, <hi>was the foundation of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land's <hi>and the Armies deliverance:</hi> Wee, that know better, denie it, and ſay, 'twas a foundation, upon which was endeavor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to bee built our ruine, if God had not mercifully preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the bringing forth and hatching of that Cockatrice egg, which your Cabals and conſpiracies had laid among us; wee ſhall not now tell you with whom. But if anie thing hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane may bee put among the foundations of our deliverance, it muſt bee the <hi>new modelling of the Armie,</hi> and putting it under a new Command, who verie well underſtood you, but could never bee brought to underſtand and entertain anie of your <hi>Cabals;</hi> they ſhamed your ſloth, and did our work without you, and put us into a condition to bee able to require ſuch an uſeleſs charge to bee gon; This is the great ſin of this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, to have thus wipe't your mouth of all the ſweet morſels your deſigns had cut out, and your hopes had alreadie ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed. They awaked you out of your dream, and you found your ſelvs hungry ſtill, and this you will never forgive them. As for the reaſons for which wee now make war upon you, the Parlament, who better know their own motives, have in their Declaration told you both them and their ends. And for the obligation by Covenant, you have been often told there is no ſuch thing in beeing, and ſhall add no more to it.</p>
            <p>But to the next, were it not that you have an evaſion in the expreſſion <hi>(the Lord's people)</hi> wee ſhould ask what is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com of all your little remnants of ſhame or ingenuitie; and wee ſhall ask you ſo ſtill, if you take this expreſſion in your
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:114588:21"/>uſual acception, <hi>viz.</hi> for all your covenanted people, were not your Parlament a covenanting People, or were not they the Lords People? give us a <hi>Criterion,</hi> by which wee may bee able to judg and diſtinguiſh them: Your Parlament decreed our <hi>Invaſion;</hi> and your whole crowd of wretched ignorant Covenanters, that ſwallow whatever you propine, <hi>invaded</hi> us in purſuance of that Act. Wee grant, you of the <hi>Kirk</hi> and your <hi>devoti</hi> did profeſs to abhor it, when you ſaw the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand fallen into hands you could not manage, and from whom you ſhould bee able to draw no advantage to your partie. Do not wee know, and all men know, that had anie intelligence of the affairs of <hi>Scotland</hi> at that time, and dare you denie it, That that <hi>Invaſion</hi> was put on by all your Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits, and all your <hi>Kirk-men</hi> unanimouſly; and the quarrel grew among your ſelvs, not upon, <hi>Whether there ſhall bee an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion,</hi> but, <hi>Who ſhall invade, and have the conduct?</hi> Are not all the pulpits of <hi>Edinburg</hi> witneſs of this? and are there not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers among us now that were ear-witneſſes? was not the work of your pulpits then to make the Sectaries odious to all your people, who knew no more of them but what you told them? and you never cared what you ſaid of them, ſo it might ſtir up the people. When you ſaw that <hi>Hamiltons</hi> partie had carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, and that you had conjured up a devil you could not command, and doubted, if hee ſhould ſucceed in <hi>England,</hi> it would not go well with you; then you began to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſ to your <hi>Balaaniſm,</hi> and fall to <hi>curſing.</hi> Wee believ you did not approve the <hi>Invaſion</hi> when it was made; but wee know verie well, and you know it too, and muſt confeſs, if your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences had power enough to make you ſpeak a truth, that if <hi>Hamilton</hi>'s Partie had not invaded, the <hi>Kirks</hi> Partie had. And do you think wee are ſo ſimple to believ that the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions</hi> of your <hi>Envie</hi> are the <hi>productions</hi> of your <hi>good affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction?</hi> And that particular diſavowings can compenſate your National Parlamentarie Enmitie. For ſhame do not thus diſcover your ignorance in the Law of Nations, and common reaſon; by which 'tis evident, when one partie break's a Treatie, the other is free; can you plaie faſt and looſ at pleaſure and keep us bound? was there anie ſuch clauſ in the Treatie that you ſhould have libertie to break it,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:114588:22"/>if you ſaw advantage; and wee bee ſ but yours, could obtrude theſe things. Suppoſe your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Parlament ſhould diſavow it, what's that to us? What juſtice, beyond the <hi>Kirk's</hi> fooliſh <hi>Stool,</hi> hath been inflicted on anie of the guiltie? or, what reparation hath there been made for all the blood and ſpoil? nay your preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament (forſooth in good time) will not own the <hi>Parlament</hi> of the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> Nor Treat about repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, till wee adnul our ſelvs. Certainly the Civilitie you quote of the <hi>Houſ of Commons</hi> to your General Aſſemblie, if anie ſuch were, was ill beſtowed, and as well requited; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, ſince it was with you but the <hi>Houſ of Commons,</hi> it ſeem's it was not the Letter or the Parlament, and therefore binde's them not. If there had been more in the Letter, then your ſelvs urge, it might yet bee reckoned among manie other of thoſe cauſleſs complements caſt away upon an ingrateful people, which you never deſerved either before or after. You that ſtood nearer your ſelvs, and knew clearly the truth of things, ſurely laught in your ſleevs at thoſe miſtakes. There are great Errors in the world about <hi>Praier,</hi> and it's efficacie; take heed of miſtakes about it: you would ſeem to intimate as if the world and the affairs thereof were managed by a <hi>power</hi> onely, without a <hi>wiſdom</hi> to direct it, which could not tell how to do well to the good, or puniſh the evil, but as your <hi>praiers,</hi> as proceeding from a principle of greater light, and more goodneſs, ſhould direct or impel. It was the going out of the mightie power of God, Ordered by his Omniſcient Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, and flowing from an infinite goodneſs and love to his people, and a juſt indignation againſt ſuch proud and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritical men, which wrought their deſtruction; as for the aeſtuations of your unſanctified anger, which you call Praier, wee cannot allow them a place in that work.</p>
            <p>When the Sectaries interpoſe with your Religion and Government in <hi>Scotland,</hi> as you do with ours, you may then teſtifie againſt them, and laie what weight you will upon your Covenant; but wee have not yet don it, and your care not to partake of the Sectaries ſins, would bee commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble (unleſs you mean <hi>Sectarianiſm</hi> it ſelf in your ſenſ) ſo as you would bee as careful to reform and repent of your
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:114588:22"/>own. Wee <hi>Invade</hi> you, not for doing your dutie, but upon grounds of cleareſt <hi>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STICE</hi> and abſolute <hi>NECES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SITIE,</hi> and recommend our Cauſ to the bleſſing of the juſt God.</p>
            <p n="9">[9] <hi>Whil'ſt wee incite men to their dutie in the defence of the Kingdom againſt invaſion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Warning.</note> 
               <hi>and encourage them in performance of the ſame, Wee deſire not to bee miſtaken, or that anie ſhould ſo far miſconſtrue our meaning as though wee did thereby intend to ſtir up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, or approve of an Invaſion of the Kingdom of</hi> England, <hi>or an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement in War againſt the ſame. In relation to peace or war in theſe Nations, wee cannot but verie much commend and approve the reſolutions of the Parlament of this Kingdom, expreſt in their Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the</hi> 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>of</hi> March <hi>to the Speaker of the Houſ of Commons, and Instructions ſent therewith to their Commiſſioners</hi> 1649, <hi>and now again renewed in another Letter to the ſame Speaker of the Houſ of Commons, wherein they acknowledg their obligations, and declare their reſolutions to obſerv the rule of Remonſtrating firſt the breaches of peace, of craving juſt reparations, of uſing all fair means, of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a preceding warning of three moneths before anie engagement in theſe Kingdoms in war, and do hold forth this waie gf procedour in clearing each others, and dealing plainly, as agreeable, not onely to particular Treaties, and to the manie Ties, Bonds, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations paſt betwixt the Kingdoms, but alſo to the Law of God, and practice of his people in his Word, and to the common law and practice of Heathen Nations, much more of Chriſtian Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anted Kingdoms: And plainly profeſs their confidence, that the Covenanted GOD of theſe Kingdoms, who did take order with theſe of this Nation, who did unlawfully engage againſt</hi> England, <hi>doth ſtill live and reign, and will bring ſhame and ruine upon what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever partie in either of theſe Nations, that without a neceſſarie cauſ, and clear calling, and without obſervance of the aforeſaid rules and order, ſhall offend and invade the other Nation: In all which wee do agree with them in our judgments and reſolutions, and conceiv that the whole Land is bound to tread the ſame ſteps, and to walk ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſame rules.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">[9] This your 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Paragraph is ſo fully anſwered in the Paper this week publiſhed. Intituled,<note place="margin">The Anſwer.</note> 
               <hi>Colonel Grey's Portman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teau opened,</hi> that wee ſhall not add a line of it more, but refer the Reader thither, this beeing but the recapitulation and <hi>Epitome</hi> of that Letter.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:114588:23"/>[10] <hi>Albeit wee bee diligently to take heed af the danger that threaten's from Sectaries,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Warning.</note> 
               <hi>and faithfully to beſtir our ſelvs in our places and ſtations in the uſe of all lawful and neceſſarie means for preventing of the ſame: Yet are wee not to forget, but alſo with the ſame diligence and care to take heed of theſe dangers and ſnares that threaten the work and people of God from Malignants. Mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnancie though a verie evil weed, yet is not pluck't up, but ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue's to bee one of the raging ſins of this Land, it beeing the ſnare wherewith looſ hearts, who cannot endure Chriſt's yoke, are moſt readily taken. Hence it is that there bee ſtill manie of that ſtamp in all the three Kingdoms, who drawing encouragements to themſelvs, from the influence they have upon the King's Counſels, and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning themſelvs in their waie, by the proceedings of Sectaries, do ſtill follow their former deſigns, and wait for their daie, and would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice in the ruine or halting of theſe who adhere to the Covenant: And experience prov'es, that manie of theſe, who have ſeem'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of, and abandon that waie, yet do not really ſhake off that ſin that hang's ſo faſt on, but upon new temptations fall again upon that ſame wickedneſs, and prove worſ then before; which may bee a caution to us not ſuddenly to truſt them. Wee make no doubt, but that Malignants will by all means endeavor that there may bee room left for them to undermine the work and people of God, and engage the Kingdom in a new War, upon terms of their deviſing, deſtructive to Religion and the Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In reference to dangers upon the right hand and upon the left, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides anie dutie alreadie repreſented to us; Wee conceiv it incumbent to us, ſeriouſly to recommend the following particulars to all the Land, eſpecially to theſe that are in truſt, either in Judicatories or Armies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Firſt to watch and praie that in nothing they bee deceived, or com ſhort of the dutie, whereunto the Lord call's them in a time of ſo manie temptations and great difficulties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Everie one would labor not onely for the knowledg of the Truth, but to have the power and love thereof engraven on their hearts, that they may from an in ward principle of grace and ſpiritual life avoid Error, and all the ſnares which lead thereunto, and bee encouraged to contend earneſtly for the Faith which God hath been pleaſed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver to his Kirk in this Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Not onely is open Malignancie to bee avoided, but men would watch that enmitie againſt the work and people of</hi> GOD, <hi>which or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily is the birth of jealouſie and diſcontent and of familiar con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſing
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:114588:23"/>with ſuch as are diſ-affected to, or lukewarm in the cauſ of</hi> GOD, <hi>ſteal not into their hearts, and gain not upon their affections by degrees; Experience almoſt of all back-ſliding times and perſons hath proved, that the fellowſhip of men of a diſ-affected or lukewarm temper, blunt's the edg of tenderneſs and zeal, and ſteal's away the heart, firſt from honeſt inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and then from the cauſ it ſelf: There have bin, &amp; are ſtill ſom in the Land, who in a cunning way of inſinuation foment jealouſies, and act di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, whilſt they ſeem to bee friends to the Cauſ, and by this means do more harm then others by open violence; Theſe wee would mark and avoid them, that wee may neither endanger our ſelvs, nor give offence unto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, nor prejudice the Cauſ of</hi> GOD.</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Wee would take diligent heed, that in nothing wee recede from the juſt and neceſſarie deſires of this Kirk and Kingdom, propounded to his Majeſtie, for ſecuring of Religion, and ſetling the peace of the Kingdom; But that wee cleav cloſely to our former reſolutions in thoſe things: If wee remit and grow ſlack, and yield in anie of them, as it ſhall increaſ the hopes and endeavors of carnal and diſ-affected men, ſo ſhall it provoke</hi> GOD <hi>againſt us to leav us to our ſelvs, till we be plunged in a pit of backſliding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>It concern's us to take heed that wee do not tread the ſteps of thoſe, who carried on the late unlawful engagement againſt the Kingdom of</hi> England <hi>in anie thing alreadie condemned by the Kirk and Kingdom, eſpecially to beware of changing the ſtate of our Cauſ, or altering the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of our quarrel, either by laying aſide of</hi> GOD's <hi>intereſt &amp; taking up of man's, or by preferring or equalling man's intereſt unto</hi> GODS; <hi>This were to turn upſide down the whole tenor of our Principles and Proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours, and not onely to ſpoil us of all the comfort wee can look for from our Covenant, but alſo to bring upon our ſelvs the guilt and reproach of all the ſin of thoſe, who carried on that engagement, ſo much condemned and born teſtimonie againſt in this Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>Wee would beware of loſing the advantage of defenders, ſeeing our ſtrength moſt conſiſt's in the equitie and clearneſs of the Cauſ, and the holie and righteous way in purſuing of the ſame: It ſhall be better for us, rather to endure ſtraits for a time, then by precipitating and making haſte in the dark, to ruſh againſt the wall and ſpoil our ſelvs of that peace and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, which wee may have in waiting till</hi> GOD <hi>go before us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7 <hi>Wee deſire that all the Land may bee ſtill pouring out their praiers and ſupplications before</hi> GOD, <hi>that the King's Majeſtie may really and wholly abandon all Malignant principles and counſels, and join cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dially in the Covenant and Cauſ of</hi> GOD.</p>
            <p n="8">8 <hi>As all the people of</hi> GOD <hi>throughout the Land would bee careful
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:114588:24"/>to diſcern of dangers and avoid ſnares from, and compliances with both Sectaries and Malignants, ſo would Miniſters bee diligent and faithful in preſsing of theſe duties, and that in a ſolid and convincing way, and labor to make it appear that they ſpeak not againſt the one or the other from paſſion or intereſt, but upon the grounds of divine reaſon, and from the light &amp; autoritie of</hi> Gods <hi>Word; that ſo they may make themſelvs ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt to the conſciences of their hearers, &amp; ſtop the mouth of gain-ſayers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Finally, all the inhabitants of the Land ſhould beware of pride and carnal confidence, and in an humble way ſhould wait upon the</hi> LORD, <hi>and tread the ſteps of holineſs and righteouſneſs, and hee who hath don great things for us, ſhall yet ſave us.</hi> A. KER.</p>
            <p n="10">[10] You judg rightlie, that there bee <hi>ſtore of Malignants,</hi> it may thank you and your <hi>Cabals,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Anſwer.</note> that wee have ſo manie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, your joyning with them and eſpouſing their Intereſt hath more ſtrengthened their hands, than anie proceedings of the Sectaries. Hath not your receiving the <hi>head of Malignants</hi> for your King, who hath been bred up in no other companie, nor followed other counſels, and whoſe heart is with them, though hee came to you to ſerv turns upon you; more hardened their hearts in their way, and animated them in their proceedings than anie thing that the Sectaries have ever don toward them. Wee com now to the particulars of your recommendation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. And to this <hi>firſt</hi> wee have nothing to ſay; but deſire that you, and wee alſo, may, without hypocriſie, do the thing you adviſe unto.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To the <hi>ſecond;</hi> if you mean by <hi>contending earneſtly for the faith,</hi> not anie uſe of outward carnal ſtrife, but an earneſt ſtrife of the ſoul in it ſelf, in the ſpirit with God, for his gracious ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of the matter of our faith, wee agree for ſo much; onely wee muſt expunge your there laſt words, conteining a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation to your Land; for you maie no more make your ſelvs a <hi>Catholick rule</hi> then <hi>Rome</hi> maie do.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Wee deſire you impartially to examine your hearts, and ſee if there bee not in you a great deal of enmitie againſt the work and people of God; which is ordinarily the work of an Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian pride; whereby you are apt to think, that you are, and that there are no other the people of God but your ſelvs; And this cauſeth your jealouſie of, and diſcontent and enmitie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt anie other that laie claim to that priviledg, if they bee not alſo of the ſame complexion with you: with whom you will
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:114588:24"/>not converſ, leaſt you ſhould bee unprejudiced, and ſo run in danger of a <hi>Kirk-cenſure,</hi> by having a better opinion perhaps of a Sectarie, and thereby have your zeal brought to a Chriſtian temper, and directed to move rationally, according to its object. Wee muſt tell you too, that there are ſom of your faction in this Land, Malignants <hi>jure divino,</hi> who by their inſinuations and ſecret infuſions, do foment faction, and ſow diviſion and diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the Government of this Common-wealth; and while they will pretend a conſcientiouſneſs, do more harm to the Peace of the Land, then the worſt of the old Malignants. Theſe wee ſhall mark, and cauſ them to avoid, or otherwiſe put them into a condition not much capable of doing us miſchief.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It had been much more your wiſdom, and your happineſs, if you had taken diligent heed to have had nothing to do with your King, who is not like to bee much bound up by the deſires of your Kirk, though you recede nothing from them; or will your Religion bee verie ſecure by it? As for the peace of your Kingdom, lookers on think you have, by eſpouſing his quarrel, made it verie difficult to eſtabliſh and ſettle. Wee in <hi>England</hi> think you have, more waies then one, provoked God, and you are like enough to bee plunged into a deep pit of a laſting miſerie.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Wee have onely here with ſad and tender hearts to lament the woful blindneſs and unſavourineſs that your <hi>formalitie</hi> and <hi>hypocriſie,</hi> by the juſt judgment of God, hath brought upon you: That upon ſo ſerious an occaſion, as this is, you ſhould have no other rule to direct your actings and forbearings by, but the condemnations of your Kirk, and your Covenant: Wee bluſh and mourn while wee read theſe paſſages. Wee Sectaries are ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalized at it; 'tis not your waie to make us your Proſelytes; For wee believ and hold forth, that the ſacred <hi>Scriptures</hi> are the <hi>rule of all things to bee believed, and to bee don.</hi> Obtrude not your Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, nor the Kirk upon us; wee ſhall condemn them both, if they either bee, or do anie thing that is contrarie to that ſacred rule. Are theſe expreſſions becoming theſe times of light? wee thought them times of darkneſs, when the Scriptures were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten; and the <hi>ſentences,</hi> the <hi>decrees,</hi> the <hi>decretals</hi> and <hi>extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gants,</hi> were made the rule of a Chriſtian faith and practice: How come's your Church to have gotten ſuch credit, that it ſhould bee emulous with <hi>Rome</hi> for <hi>infallibilitie?</hi> Accuſtom your ſelvs therefore to Canonical language; and talk not of Gods inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:114588:25"/>while you meaſure it not by God's Word; though by the waie wee muſt tell you, that word <hi>Intereſt</hi> ſounded with God, is hardly concord in our ears.</p>
            <p n="6">6. You loſt your advantage and defence, when you became <hi>Invaders;</hi> you ſhould have needed no <hi>defence</hi> againſt us, if you had not begun to <hi>invade,</hi> and proceed in ſuch waies as declare you ſtill <hi>enemies.</hi> If you had been righteous, it had been well for your ſelvs and us too; and when you are brought to a conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to bee ſo unrighteous no more, and that wee have ſuch an aſſurance of it, as you cannot break, wee ſhall not deſire longer to purſue you; and if this tenderneſs of not moving till God goe's before you, had poſſeſſed your Parlament in 1648, wee are confident you had never invaded <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. By this it ſeem's, you are not ſure of your King; your ſelvs doubt, whether hee bee real or not, and free from malignant principles? What meant you to bee troubled with him upon theſe uncertain terms? here was ſomthing at the bottom wil finde you out at laſt: You were in the beginning of you paper verie tender of joining with Malignants, or having anie in your Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie; why not ſo, as well as have an Armie for a Malignant? for it ſeem's your ſelvs dare not undertake hee is not one.</p>
            <p n="8">8 Wee wholy like your Counſel to your Miniſters, and wiſh you would take the ſame Courſ the next Papers you Emit; then perhaps wee might receiv ſom information or conviction; for wee profeſs our ſelvs readie to receiv it, when from thoſe grounds and principles; and wee would have you define or deſcribe a <hi>Seclarie,</hi> and tell us wherein is the poyſon of their opinions, and practice; for the name hath no harm in it. And wee begin to take it up and wear it verie contentedly: it ſeem's to us alſo that manie of thoſe men you ſo call are of the beſt among us, God hath honor'd them to do great ſervice to this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for that cauſ wee both love and honor them, and think wee have greater reaſon to do ſo, becauſ you hate them, for wee know you purſue an intereſt quite contrarie to ours.</p>
            <p n="9">9. In this you are ſhort, you ſhould have added <hi>hypocriſie</hi> to your <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>carnal confidence.</hi> And truly if they would leav off their <hi>ſwearing, uncleanneſs</hi> and <hi>drunkenneſs</hi> among you, which is ſo verie ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, it would do well. And if in a deep and true humilitie they would retire into themſelvs, and ſearch their hearts, and turn from all their evil waies and walk in the waies of righteouſneſs, and holineſs (a thing much ſpoken of, and arrogated by manie that neither have it, nor un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what 'tis) and meet the Lord in the <hi>waie of his judgments,</hi> and endeavor to agree with their adverſarie while hee is in the way, yee may vet bee ſafe, which would bee verie deſirable, ſo wee may bee ſatisfied and ſafe alſo.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
